<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A counterpoison against couetousnes in a sermon preached at Pauls-Crosse, May 23. 1619. By Ier. Dyke minister of Gods word at Epping in Essex.</title>
            <author>Dyke, Jeremiah, 1584-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116229</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851446</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851446</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16720</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21043)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16720)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1096:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A counterpoison against couetousnes in a sermon preached at Pauls-Crosse, May 23. 1619. By Ier. Dyke minister of Gods word at Epping in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Dyke, Jeremiah, 1584-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Richard Field] for Robert Mylbourne, and are to be sold at his shop at the great south doore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Luke XII, 15.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A counterpoyson against couetousnesse.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through; some leaves cropped at head.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16720:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16720:1"/>
            <p>A COVNTERPOISON AGAINST COVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TOVSNES: In a Sermon preached at Pauls-Croſſe, May 23. 1619.</p>
            <p>By IER. DYKE Miniſter of Gods word <hi>at Epping in Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 119. 36.</bibl> 
               <hi>Incline mine heart vnto thy teſtimonies, and not vnto couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Auguſt. in Pſal. 128.</bibl> 
               <hi>Auaritia opus eſt mali hominis, homo ipſe opus Dei. Et quid vult Deus? Occidere in te quod ipſe feciſti, &amp; ſaluare te quem ipſe fecit.</hi>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Milborne</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for ROBERT MYLBOVRNE, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the great South doore of Pauls.</p>
            <p>1619.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16720:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16720:2"/>
            <head>A COVNTERPOYSON AGAINST COVETOVSNES:</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>LVKE 12. 15.</bibl>
               <q>And he ſaid vnto them, Take heed and beware of couetouſneſſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O better fared it ſometimes with our Lord himſelfe in his miniſtery, then it now dayly doth with vs his ſeruants the miniſters of the Goſpell: and no better with vs then it did with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Ezek. 33. 31. His auditors ſate before him as the Lords people, they heard his words, they would not do them, <hi>their hearts ran after their couetouſneſſe.</hi> Such is the dunghilly diſpoſition of many hearers, that euen then their hearts are moſt eagerly bent vpon their earthly intentions, when Gods miniſters labour moſt of all to call them off, and to raiſe them vp to heauenly contemplations. It was iuſt thus with an auditour of our Sauiours in this preſent chapter; whileſt this bleſſed ſeeds-man, euen the Lord of the field himſelfe was committing his ſeed to the earth, behold ſome falles vpon <hi>thornie ground.</hi> Whileſt our Sauiour was labouring to prepare men for an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, here was one whoſe heart ran after a temporall inheritance, and amidſt our Sauiours heauenly, his thoughts are taken vp with an earthly buſineſſe. Nay
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16720:3"/> he cannot reſt there neither; he doth not onely <hi>mind earthly things,</hi> as they, Philip. 3, but this ſore breakes out in his lips: for, verſe 13. <hi>One of the company ſaid, Maiſter ſpeake to my brother that he diuide the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with me.</hi> This earthly minded man cannot be content with thoſe, Ezechiel 33. 31. to haue his <hi>heart runne,</hi> but that which is worſe, his <hi>tongue</hi> muſt <hi>runne</hi> too; and that which is yet the ſore of all, euen then when our Sauiour is employed in the diſpenſation of the word, euen then is he thus bold with a ſawcie importunity to trouble and interrupt our Lord in this ſacred ſeruice. How iump and iuſt is this fellowes faith and religion with thouſands of our times, who will vphold it for a truth, that a miniſter may do God better ſeruice in taking vp quarrels betweene neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and compoſing differences betweene pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, then with all his paines in preaching. This is right to call Chriſt from <hi>diuiding the word</hi> to the <hi>diuiding of an inheritance.</hi> Oh maiſter, you might do well to ceaſſe this trouble to your ſelfe and this great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, to make an end of your Sermon, and to come and end a difference betweene me and my brother; you ſhall do a worke of charitie, and a neighbourly good office betweene vs, you may ſaue a great deale that may otherwiſe be idlely ſpent in law. Ridiculous follie! As if ſo be the ſauing of the purſe were to be preferred, were to be regarded, before the ſauing of ſoules.</p>
            <p>Well, but what is our Sauiours anſwer? His an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt <hi>particular,</hi> verſe 14. <hi>He ſaid vnto him.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly more <hi>ſeuerall,</hi> verſe 15. <hi>He ſaid vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:16720:3"/> 1. His <hi>particular</hi> anſwer is a perſonall checke to this mans importunity and demand both: <hi>He ſaid vnto him, Man, who hath made me a Iudge &amp; a diuider ouer you?</hi> And ſo he <hi>anſwers not the foole according to his follie,</hi> refuſeth to gratifie him in this his vnſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and vnlawfull requeſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His <hi>ſeuerall</hi> anſwer is to the whole multitude: <hi>And he ſaid vnto them, Take heed and beware of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe,</hi> verſe 15. And thus our Sauiour doth <hi>anſwer the foole according to his follie,</hi> and takes occaſion by his folly to teach the whole multitude wiſedome. The roote of this mans folly was couetouſneſſe: the ſtrong ſauour where of our Lord ſented in this his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable requeſt. Chriſt therefore layeth the axe to the roote of the tree, and ſmiteth at the maine radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call corruption of his heart. And ſo anſwers him not according to his <hi>Deſire,</hi> but according to his <hi>Neede.</hi> Therein following Gods owne rule, Ezech. 14. 4. that he that comes to the Prophet with a queſtion, what euer his queſtion be, ſhould be anſwered not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his <hi>curioſities,</hi> but according to his <hi>neceſſities;</hi> he muſt be anſwered <hi>according to his Idols,</hi> he muſt heare roundly and plainly of that ſin whereof he was chiefly guiltie. Thus deales the Lord here. And not onely ſo, but of his poyſon makes triacle, &amp; preſcribes a bleſſed preſeruatiue againſt that peſtilence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with this mans heart was infected. Such was his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie handineſſe and dexterity, to make euill the riſe and hint of good, and to extract heauenly light out of the darkneſſe of an earthly heart.</p>
            <p>And thus we ſee in briefe how theſe words frame and fall in with the body of the text.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16720:4"/>
            <p> The words themſelues are a <hi>Caution</hi> againſt <hi>Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe.</hi> In the which we haue three things conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>manner</hi> of the caution. <hi>Take heed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>obiect</hi> of it. <hi>Of couetouſneſſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The <hi>perſons</hi> warned to beware. <hi>And he ſaid vnto them.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>manner</hi> of this caution lieth in the <hi>Duplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> thereof. <hi>Take heede and beware.</hi> Not <hi>take heede</hi> alone, nor <hi>beware</hi> alone, but both <hi>take heede, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.</hi> Now what meanes this double fence? might not a ſingle <hi>item</hi> haue ſerued the turne? Certainly he that telleth vs that we muſt be accountant for euery idle word, would not himſelfe be guiltie therof. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what therfore there is in it that the cautio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is doubled; yea not onely doubled, but in a manner trebled, in as much as the ſecond word ſeemeth to haue a double weight aboue the firſt. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The firſt word implying an ocular warineſſe, an <hi>eye watch;</hi> the ſecond, an <hi>hand watch,</hi> a kind of manuall, if not a martiall and preſidiary guarding of a mans ſelfe. Mark, 8. 15. Chriſt giuing his diſciples warning of the leauen of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, vſeth two words alſo, but yet the latter there ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be of no greater force then the former. It is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. But here not onely the word, but the weight is doubled, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Take heede and beware.</hi> As if he had ſaid, to paraphraſe the text, not to mend the tranſlation, <hi>Watch</hi> and <hi>ward,</hi> nay <hi>watch</hi> and <hi>guard,</hi> and defend your ſelues from the ſinne of couetouſneſſe. Well. What may all this meane now? It ſeemes to argue theſe particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:16720:4"/> 1. A wondrous ſtrong <hi>inclination</hi> in our corrupt natures to this ſinne. If our affections were not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and headſtrong, a ſingle reyne would haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to haue courbed and bridled vs in. If we were not eagerly bent thereon, what ſhould neede pikes and halbards to keepe vs off?</p>
            <p n="2">2. A wondrous great <hi>danger</hi> in the ſinne. If it were not a deepe and a dangerous bog, a ſlighter fence might haue ſerued, this double pale might haue bene ſpared. Prou. 4. 14. 15, you haue an whole heape of prohibitions againſt the wayes of wicked men: <hi>Enter not into the path of the wicked, go not in the way of euill men; auoyde it, paſſe not by it, turne from it, paſſe away.</hi> What meanes this frequent and vehement iteration, and inculcation of one and the ſame thing? It ſerues to teach both our proneneſſe vnto, and the perill in thoſe wayes. Iuſt ſo it is here. Our Sauiours vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in forewarning vs, argues the more then ordinary perill of this ſinne. This double caueat argues more then a ſingle danger therein.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A wondrous carefull <hi>watch</hi> that we ſhould keepe ouer our owne hearts, that at no time they be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with the couetous cares of this life. Since our inclination is ſo great, and the danger no leſſe then it, our watch ſhould be proportionable to both, double and double. Some dangers are auoyded by the bare eſpiall, it is enough <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſee them. But here not onely eyes, but weapons are required; here we muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not onely haue our eyes in our heads, but our weapons in our hands. The danger of the ſinne and inclination of our hearts thereto being ſo great, here it is true, that <hi>Abundans cautela non nocet.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:16720:5"/> If this which is double in precept, were quadruple in practiſe, it were all little and little enough.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Point; the <hi>obiect</hi> of the caution. What it is wherof we muſt take heed &amp; beware: take heed &amp; beware <hi>of couetouſneſſe.</hi> Couetouſneſſe is the ſin then, of which our Sauiour here forewarnes vs. A ſinne, I make no queſtion but hath often bene witneſſed againſt in this place. Giue me leaue alſo to adde my teſtimony, that ſo in the mouth of many witneſſes, <hi>yea of a cloud of witneſſes,</hi> this truth may ſtand.</p>
            <p>We haue here then a watchword againſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe: Take heede and beware of couetouſneſſe. A ſin indeed that ill beſeemes, and in no wiſe will ſuite with the profeſſion of the name of Chriſt. <hi>Let euery one that calles vpon the name of the Lord,</hi> &amp; vpon whom the name of the Lord is called, <hi>depart from iniquity,</hi> 2. Tim. 2. 19. but eſpecially from that <hi>iniquitie</hi> which hath caſt vpon riches, otherwiſe Gods good bleſſings, the reprochfull title of the <hi>riches of iniquitie,</hi> Luk. 16.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>conuerſation</hi> muſt be as <hi>becomes the Goſpell,</hi> Phil. 1. 27. But how may that be done? Heb. 13. 5. ye haue a comment to that text. <hi>Let your conuerſation be without couetouſneſſe.</hi> When our <hi>conuerſation</hi> is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>couetouſneſſe,</hi> then is our <hi>conuerſation</hi> as <hi>becometh the Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>conuerſation?</hi> nay our very <hi>communication</hi> muſt be free from it. Epheſ. 5. 3. <hi>Fornication and all vncleanneſſe, and</hi> couetouſneſſe, <hi>let it not be once</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>amongſt you, as becomes Saints.</hi> It becomes Saints to walke as becomes the Goſpell; they then walke as becomes the Goſpell, when both <hi>conuerſation</hi> and <hi>communication</hi> are free from <hi>couetouſneſſe.</hi> So ſpeakes
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16720:5"/> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> of couetouſneſſe as <hi>Dauid</hi> of idols, Pſal. 16. 4. <hi>I will not make mention of their</hi> names <hi>with my lips.</hi> If the <hi>name,</hi> how much more ſhould the <hi>thing</hi> be odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous? Our <hi>conuerſation?</hi> our <hi>communication?</hi> yea our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>cogitations</hi> ſhould be free from it. It is the brand of thoſe brute beaſts that are made to be taken and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, of curſed children, 2. Pet. 2. 14: that they haue <hi>their hearts,</hi> and ſo their thoughts <hi>exerciſed to couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take we a view of all the Saints and ſeruants of God, whoſe memories, whoſe graces, yea and whoſe ſinnes are recorded in holy writ; ſee if you can finde me one of all that bleſſed company, that was euer ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed with this filth, that was euer defiled with this mire. Indeed once <hi>Noah</hi> was ouertaken with the loue of <hi>wine,</hi> neuer with the loue of the <hi>world.</hi> Once <hi>Lot</hi> was twice <hi>inceſtuous,</hi> neuer <hi>couetous.</hi> Once <hi>Dauid</hi> was beſotted with the <hi>fleſh,</hi> neuer bewitched with the <hi>world,</hi> but euen in the top of the worlds happineſſe acknowledgeth himſelfe a ſtranger and a pilgrime, 1. Chron. 29. 15. Once <hi>Peter</hi> denyed his maiſter, but yet it was not the loue of the world (for he had denyed that before he denyed his maiſter, in forſaking all,) but the feare of the world that cauſed him to ſlip into that ſin. <hi>Zaecheus</hi> indeed before his conuerſion had bene a couetous pinching prolling publican; but no ſooner doth he take Chriſt by the hand, but the firſt thing he doth is to ſhake hands with his couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Chriſt that hath bid vs beware of it, will much more himſelfe take heed and beware of dwelling in that heart, where that ſinne dwels. If he whip not this money merchant out of the temple of our heart,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16720:6"/> it will keepe and barre out him for taking any poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion there.</p>
            <p>Now what, thinke we, may be the reaſon that theſe forenamed Scripture-ſaints, though they had their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both infirmities and groſſe ſinnes, yet were ſtill free from this? Seemes it not to aduiſe thus much? That grace and religion may better ſtand with once-acted adulterie, inceſt, and drunkenneſſe, then it can with that habituall iniquity of couetouſneſſe? <hi>Dauids</hi> adulterie, <hi>Noahs</hi> drunkenneſſe, <hi>Lots</hi> inceſt, theſe were actuall ſinnes but once acted, they were no habituall euils in them. A man may fall into theſe ſinnes, and yet not be an habituated ſinner. But a man cannot properly be couetous without an habitual continued euill diſpoſition of the ſoule. Now this is a ſure rule, that grace may ſtand with ſome actual though groſſe ſinne, being but once ſlipt into (though but one actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſinne doth ſhrewdly wound and weaken grace:) but whether grace and a good heart can ſtand with a continued habituall wickedneſſe, there is the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, if ſo be a queſtion.</p>
            <p>Hence haply therefore hath it bene, that diuerſe of the Saints of God when they haue bene to iuſtifie their integritie, and make good their reputation, haue euermore bene eſpecially carefull to free themſelues from the imputation of this ſinne, and haue ſhaken off not this duſt, but dirt and filth from off their hands and feete. Thus <hi>Samuel</hi> in his apologie, 1. Sam. 12. 3. So <hi>Ieremie,</hi> Ier. 15. 10. <hi>Wo is me my mother, thou haſt borne me a contentious man that ſtriueth with the whole earth; I haue neither lent on vſurie, nor men haue lent to me on vſurie, yet euery one doth curſe me.</hi> Well he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16720:6"/> thought they might haue curſed him, had he bene guilty of that curſed ſinne; but he ſhewes the worlds iniquitie by his owne honeſty, and his owne honeſty in being free from the fruits of that ſinne of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe. So <hi>Paule</hi> Acts 20. 33. <hi>I haue coueted no mans ſiluer, nor gold, nor apparell.</hi> Now why purge theſe men rather from this then from other ſinnes? why purge they not from adultery, whoredome, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? but ſpecially, and in a manner from couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Surely becauſe full well they knew, that of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinnes this is that which moſt ſtaynes and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſheth good report and honeſt reputation, and ſtandeth in greateſt oppoſition to the life and truth of grace.</p>
            <p>For where this ſinne getteth head, it eateth out the heart of grace, by eating all grace out of the heart. <hi>While ſome haue luſted after money they haue</hi> erred <hi>from the faith.</hi> 1. Tim. 6. 10. Nay they haue not ſtayd there, but haue fallen from the faith. 2. Tim. 4. 10, <hi>Demas hath</hi> forſaken <hi>me, and hath embraced this preſent world.</hi> It ſo fares with earthly minds as with the earth in which are the mines of ſiluer and gold; of all earths they are obſerued to be the moſt barren; and of all hearts ſuch are the moſt fruitleſſe, the moſt grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe. Therefore in the parable the cares of this life are compared to <hi>thornes;</hi> thornes choke the good ſeed. As well may a man looke for an harueſt in an hedge, as for grace in a couetous heart. Theſe couetous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are the ſeuen ill-fauoured empty eares that eate vp the full and good eares. Theſe are the caterpillers, and graſhoppers, the canker and palmer wormes that conſume the greene herbe of grace in the field of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16720:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16720:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:16720:8"/> heart. The dampes of the earth do not more quench fire, then the loue of the earth dampes grace. And indeed no wonder that this ſinne is ſuch an enemy vnto grace; for it is an enemy vnto, and a ſcorner of the meanes of grace, the preaching of the word. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek. 33. 31. <hi>They ſit before thee, and they heare thy words, but they will not do them.</hi> What was the reaſon? <hi>Their heart runneth after their couetouſneſſe.</hi> But that is not all, behold yet a greater abomination then this. It teacheth men not only to diſobey, but to deſpiſe, and mocke at the word. Luke 16. 14. <hi>And the Phariſes alſo who were</hi> couetous <hi>heard theſe things,</hi> namely our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours Sermon againſt the ſeruice of Mammon, and what was the ſucceſſe? <hi>And they</hi> derided <hi>him.</hi> Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe is a profane ſinne that ſeateth a man in the chaire of peſtilence, in the ſcorners pew.</p>
            <p>We find a prohibition, Pro. 23. 6. not to eate of a couetous mans bread. A reaſon is ſecretly couched in that epithete there giuen him: Eate not the bread of him that hath <hi>an euill eye.</hi> He hath an euil eye, which makes him wiſh a man choakt, when he bids, much good may it do him. Such euill and counterfeit wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſhould make a man take little pleaſure in table-friendſhip and familiarity with him. But yet there is a greater reaſon then this, that ſhould make vs ſhy of his conuerſe, namely the feare of the defilement of his pitch. Couetouſneſſe is a defiling ſinne, Marke 7. 21. 22. <hi>Thefts, couetouſneſſe, theſe come from within, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file the man.</hi> Yea it ſo defiles, as that in that regard we ſhould auoyd ouer familiar conuerſe with him. And vpon this ground doth <hi>Paul</hi> forbid eating his bread; 1. Corint. 5. 11. <hi>If any man that is called a brother be</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16720:8"/> couetous, <hi>with ſuch an one no not to eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The world would faine hold that doctrine of <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall</hi> ſinnes ſtill; and though Popery it ſelfe which firſt hatcht that diſtinction, do ranke this amongſt their <hi>mortall</hi> ſinnes, yet would men haue it but a veniall triuiall offence. For a man to be an adulterer, a forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator, I hope the world is not growne to that deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate paſſe yet; but I may adde, to be a ſwearer, and a drunkard, theſe are counted, and indeed they are hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous abominations. But for a man to be couetous, this is ſlighted ouer as a matter of nothing. I he ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie language of the world is, He is a man ſomewhat with the hardeſt, a little with the neareſt, a little too much for the world, but yet a maruellous honeſt, a wondrous good man. Now in good truth were it not ridiculous to ſay ſo of a thiefe? of an adulterer? Why not then as ridiculous to ſay ſo of the couetous? For as honeſt a man as the world makes him, yet God ſtill rankes him amongſt the moſt heynous and tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent tranſgreſſors. Beſides thoſe places, Marke 7. 21. 22, and Epheſ. 5. 3. 5, conſider theſe two places, 1. Cor. 5. 11. 1. Cor. 6. 9. 10. In both which places ye ſhall find the couetous in the middeſt of the throng crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp on both ſides with <hi>fornicators, idolaters, ſodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, theeues, drunkards, reuilers, and extortioners.</hi> God would let vs ſee by his companions with whom he ſorts him, what to thinke of his honeſty. Nay yet to helpe the matter, and to let you ſee the full honeſty of this ſinne, note it, and with horrour note it you that are guiltie, that the Apoſtle makes it a Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, and ſigne of a reprobate ſenſe. Twentie and two of them are there in all, and this is ſet in the fourth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:16720:9"/> place, Rom. 1. 29. <hi>Wherefore God gaue them ouer to a reprobate minde.</hi> But how appeared it? Being filled with all vnrighteouſneſſe, fornication, wickedneſſe, <hi>couetouſneſſe.</hi> Thus how light and ſlight ſoeuer this ſinne be in the worlds eſteeme, yet behold how weightie and ponderous it is in the ballance and ſcales of the Sanctuary.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but moſt mens iudgements will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to this truth, but conſcience is not ſo ſoone wrought to obedience, and the truth will ſooner be confeſſed then practiſed; therefore to bring men to the practiſe of this confeſſed truth, I will commend to your Chriſtian conſiderations theſe three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>What</hi> couetouſneſſe is.</item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Danger</hi> of it.</item>
               <item>3. The <hi>Remedies</hi> againſt it.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What</hi> couetouſneſſe is. This is a point ſo much the rather to be enquired after, becauſe though a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous man will acknowledge couetouſneſſe to be a ſinne, yet by no meanes will he acknowledge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be couetous. So that a man may ſay of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous man as <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeakes of an hypocrite, that he is <hi>tale monſtrum quod eſt ſimpliciter impeceabile,</hi> a ſinleſſe kind of monſter that by no meanes will be borne downe to be guiltie. An adulterer, a drunkard, a ſwearer, theſe ſinners and ſinnes are eaſily diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, eaſily conuinced, theſe openly weare Satans cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſance, theſe are palpable impieties. But this, it is a ſculking iniquitie, it will needs be a vertuous vice, a gracious ſinne. <hi>Paul</hi> hath a phraſe, 1. Theſſal. 2. 5. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>coloured couetouſneſſe,</hi> or as our new
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16720:9"/> tranſlators, <hi>the cloke of couetouſneſſe.</hi> It is a colouring, and a cloking ſinne. It is a ſinne that weares the <hi>cloke</hi> and liuery of thrift, prouidence, good husbandrie, honeſt care for a mans owne, without which a man is worſe then an infidell. It is fit therefore that this falſe colour and complexion be waſhed off, and that this monſter be vncloked and vncaſed, that his euill fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, but naturall lineaments, may appeare.</p>
            <p>There be two words then in Scripture which ſeeme to expreſſe the full nature of this ſinne.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. This word in my text, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>2. That word of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. Tim. 6. 10, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Loue of money.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Some define it by the firſt, to be a deſire of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more. But yet with their good leaues I deſire to haue ſomewhat more in the definition thereof; for euery deſire of hauing more is not couetouſneſſe. A man may pray <hi>Agurs</hi> prayer without couetouſneſſe. A man in a low and meane condition may deſire of God with condition to haue his eſtate bettered, and yet not be couetous. Others therefore adde, and make it to be an inordinate deſire of hauing more, by vniuſt and vnlawfull meanes. But that is too fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for then ſhould none be couetous but vniuſt get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of goods. A man may be couetous, and yet get his goods without fraud, oppreſſion, and coſinage. Therefore not to trouble you with many, me thinkes that of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hits the nayle on the head aboue all <note place="margin">Auaritia eſt plus velle quàm ſat eſt. <hi>Aug. de lib. arb. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 17. Quid eſt auaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe? Progredi vltra quàm ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit.</note> others: <hi>Couetouſneſſe is the deſire of more then enough.</hi> To deſire beyond the bounds of ſufficiencie, to ſeeke for more then a man may pray for, Giue vs this day <hi>our daily bread,</hi> to ſeeke and labour for ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16720:10"/> this is couetouſneſſe. A man, I take it, may be ſaid to haue enough, when he hath ſuch a portion <note place="margin">Tantum autem ſat eſt quantum ſibi exigit natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae in ſuo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re conſeruandae modus. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </note> and ſufficiencie of theſe outward things, as that he hath wherewith to liue plentifully, as alſo both to traine vp his liberally for the beſt imployments, and to leaue his liberally according to their callings and conditions. I thinke ſuch a man may be ſaid to haue enough, and what is more is of ſinne. No ſooner doth a man ſteppe ouer the hedge and pale of <hi>ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie,</hi> but he is preſently in the wide, wilde, and boundleſſe champian of <hi>couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the loue of money.</hi> And thus a man may be couetous in the inordinate loue of that which he hath, though he go not beyond the limits of ſufficiencie. There is a couetouſneſſe in <hi>ſcraping,</hi> that may be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and there is a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe in <hi>holding,</hi> that may be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. There is a couetouſneſſe in <hi>rapacitie,</hi> that comes from a deſire of more then enough. There is a couetouſneſſe in <hi>te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacitie,</hi> that comes from an immoderate loue of that we haue. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hath a large paw to get and gather more then enough. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is like the man in the Goſpell with the withered hand, whoſe ſinewes are ſo ſhrunke vp that he is not able to reach forth his hand to any worke of pietie or pitty. The firſt is more properly the rich mans couetouſneſſe; with the ſecond may a poore man be couetous. I am not ſo preciſe in my diſtinction, but that theſe two may be confounded; for indeed the firſt cannot be without the laſt, though it be poſſible the laſt may be without the firſt. So that lay both theſe together, and we haue the nature of this ſinne. <hi>It is an inordinate loue of, and</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:16720:10"/> 
               <hi>a deſire after theſe outward things beyond the bounds of ſufficiencie.</hi> Now beſides the inward, peſtilent, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous nature thereof, there be certaine outward ſymptomes, in which as in ſo many plague-ſores it breakes forth and diſcouers it ſelfe. They among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others are theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Ioh. 3. 31. <hi>He that is of the earth, is of the earth, and he ſpeakes of the earth.</hi> His breath like a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mans is euer of a ſtrong earthy ſauour. His lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is, Pſal. 4. <hi>Who will ſhew vs any good?</hi> Corne and wine, ſheepe and oxen, marketable and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantable commodities are euermore the ſubiect of his diſcourſe. It is euer market, and exchange time with him. Seldome or neuer with the vertuous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Pro. 31. doth he <hi>open his mouth with wiſedome,</hi> neither is <hi>the law of grace in his lips.</hi> That looke as it is ſaid of the righteous man, Pſal. 37. 30. 31. <hi>The mouth of the righteous will ſpeake of wiſedome, and his tongue will talke of iudgement, for the law of his God is in his heart;</hi> ſo may it be ſaid of the couetous, His mouth will ſpeake of worldlineſſe, and his tongue will talke of earthlineſſe, for the loue of his god is in his heart. There is earth at his heart, and his very breath ſmels of it. Their Egyptian garlicke which they haue ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed riſeth in their ſtomackes, and makes them to belch, and to bring vp a filthy ſtinking vnſauourie <note place="margin">Nam ſi ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ſummo Ioui, Atque in mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus extateneam vt po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riciam: interea loci, Si lucri quid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, potius rem diuina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deſeram. <hi>Plaut. in Pſeudol.</hi>
               </note> breath.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He keepes a court of Faculties in his conſcience, he can giue himſelfe a <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> to be free from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dutie of Gods worſhip and ſeruice, if it be to ſerue his owne turne. He is none of your preciſe Sabbata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians. He ſcruples not to loſe Sermons, to trauell to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:16720:11"/> ſhew and ſell his wares as well on the Sabboth as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dayes. It is no trouble to his conſcience to bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine and barter vpon the Sabboth as familiarly as vpon any other day. He eſteemes his country Church euery whit as great a conuenience as the Citie Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, where he may meete many of his neighbors, and diſpatch many buſineſſes at once without a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trouble of going to their ſeuerall houſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He is ſometimes <hi>homo omnium artium,</hi> a man of many callings and profeſſions, he will haue an iron in euery fire, an hand in euery buſineſſe, and euen ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loades himſelfe with a multitude of employments. He will needs be a temporall pluraliſt, will haue as many farmes as he hath fingers, will be a Miniſter and a Phyſition, a citie merchant, and a countrey farmer; and ſo peſters and clogs himſelfe with a multitude of buſineſſe, that he hath but a little time for ſleepe, and none at all for God, but what his couetouſneſſe to ſaue a tweluepenny mulct will affoord him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He is ſometimes againe a man <hi>nullius artis,</hi> a man of no calling. He giues ouer his multitude of farmes and employments, not out of conſcience, but out of a deſire of greater eaſe and ſecurity. For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience though it forbid encombrance, yet it requires employment. But he flies from one extreame to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, from many callings and employments to none at all, and betakes himſelfe to a courſe wherein he may liue with leſſe faith and greater ſecurity. From hyring of farmes he falles to letting of money, and ſo comes to be of the number of thoſe men, of whom if ten in an hundred chance to go to heauen, yet an hundred to ten are ſure to go to hell.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:16720:11"/> 2. Thing the <hi>danger</hi> of couetouſneſſe. We haue here a double caution againſt this ſinne. As is the <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſo is the <hi>danger,</hi> double. Yea this double cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion implies the danger, if not the double danger. This ſinne therefore is doubly <hi>dangerous.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In the <hi>ſinnes</hi> it breedes.</item>
               <item>2. In the <hi>puniſhments</hi> it brings.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>ſinnes</hi> it breeds. It is a mother iniquitie that giues life to many a foule ſinne. Ten Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements hath almighty God giuen vs, and this is an vniuerſall breach, and breaker of them all. Indeed there is no ſinne but it may be ſaid to breake them all, for he that breakes one is guiltie of the breach of the whole Law, Iames 2. 10. becauſe one ſinne doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and <hi>habitually</hi> diſpoſe the mind to any ſinne. But this doth <hi>actually</hi> tranſgreſſe them all. Pleaſe you in briefe to runne them ouer, and ſee how.</p>
            <p>1. Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt haue none other gods before me.</hi> But the couetous Mammoniſt he hath <note place="margin">Non adoro, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit. Quare? quia teipſum non inflectis, &amp; incuruas? multo magis adoras per facta, &amp; res ipſas. Haec enim eſt maior ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio, &amp; vt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas vide in Deo. Quinam enim eum magis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorant, ijne qui ſolum ſtant in precibus, an qui faciunt eius vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem? <hi>Chryſ. ad Epheſ. hom.</hi> 18</note> other, and he ſerues other gods then the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, euen gods of the earth, gods of mettall, idols of ſiluer, and idols of gold. That as the Prophet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines of the Iewes, Ier. 2. 28. <hi>According to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thy cities are thy gods ô Iudah,</hi> ſo may we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine of the couetous: According to the number of his bags, nay of his pence, is the number of his idols. And therefore no maruell that the Apoſtle, Coloſ. 3. 5. calls couetouſneſſe <hi>idolatrie,</hi> and Epheſ. 5. 5. the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous an <hi>idolater.</hi> For though he ſacrifice not beaſts to his idoll, yet that which is worſe, he ſacrifices his ſoule and himſelfe; and though he fall not downe vpon his knees and pray not to his ſiluer, yet as the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16720:12"/> profane Atheiſt hath ſaid in his heart, <hi>There is no God,</hi> Pſal. 14. 1: ſo the couetous Mammoniſt ſayeth in his heart, This is my god; he ſayeth to his wedge, <hi>Thou art my confidence,</hi> Iob 31. 24. And howſoeuer his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe enioyne him ſorer and ſharper labor, more dangerous and deſperate aduentures then euer God requires in his ſeruice, yet is it willingly and chereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obeyed, and <hi>obedience is better then ſacrifice,</hi> 1. Sam. 15. 22: yea it hath both <hi>obedience</hi> and <hi>ſacrifice.</hi> Hab. 1. 16 <hi>They</hi> ſacrifice <hi>vnto their net.</hi> His golden idoll hath the loue, confidence, truſt, affiance, and obedience of <note place="margin">Et inter alia eius nomina quod Pecuma vocare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Et Pecunia, inquiunt, voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eo quòd eius ſint omnia. O magnam ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem diuini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mims? Sed ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirum hoc a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaritia Ioui no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men impoſuit, vt quiſquis amat pecuniam, non quemlibet De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ſed ipſum regem omnium ſibi amare vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deatur. Qualis ergo iſta theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia debet eſſe ſapienti, vbi rex deorum eius rei nomen accepit quam nemo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piens concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. <hi>Auguſt. de Ciuit. Dei. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> his heart; which are the things the firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment claimes for Gods part. The goddeſſe <hi>Pecunia</hi> was one of the idols of old heathen Rome, and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> reports) was one of the many names their <hi>Iupiter</hi> had. Euery Mammoniſt is a profeſſor of this paganiſh religion: if at leaſt it be not worſe to giue vnto <hi>money</hi> the worſhip of <hi>God,</hi> then vnto <hi>God</hi> the name of <hi>money.</hi> The fond Iſraelites made them an idoll of the Egyptians iewels, and then dance about it, (one calfe about another) and ſacrifice vnto it, and ſay, <hi>Theſe be thy gods ô Iſrael.</hi> Such a calfe, ſuch a ſot is the couetous; when he hath ſcraped together the worlds iewels, he makes them his idols, &amp; ſayeth in his heart, Theſe be thy gods, ô my ſoule, to whom thou oweſt thy loue, ſeruice and affectionate obedience. And ſo makes himſelfe a groſſe and notorious tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor of this firſt Law.</p>
            <p>2. Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen image,</hi> &amp;c. A commandement that enioynes the puritie of Gods outward worſhip, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands maintenance, and forbideth the corruption
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16720:12"/> thereof. But in this is he as foule as in the former. This corruption of the heart hath euer bene that which hath vſhered corruptions into Gods Church &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Therefore are theſe two ioyned together. Eſay 2. 6. 7: <hi>Their land was full of ſiluer and gold, and there was none end of their treaſures: Their land alſo was full of idols, they worſhipped the worke of their owne hands.</hi> It is no wonder that couetouſneſſe in the breach of the firſt, ſhould prepare and make way for the breach of the ſecond Commandement in groſſe idolatrie. What made <hi>Demetrius</hi> runne roaring and rauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſtreets of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and crying, <hi>Great is Diana of the Epheſians,</hi> but meerly the loue of his purſe? <hi>Sirs, ye know that by this craft we get our goods, and that craft brought in great gaines vnto the craftſmen</hi> It was the <hi>great gaine</hi> that made <hi>Diana</hi> ſo great, and made him make ſo great noiſe for her. What brought in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the hooke with the three teeth, 1. Sam. 2. 13. but this hooking and catching ſinne of couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</p>
            <p>What made the Temple in our Sauiour time <hi>a den of theeues?</hi> Euen that ſinne that made the Prieſts theeues, the ſame ſinne that made <hi>Iudas</hi> a theefe. It was the couetouſneſſe of the Prieſts that admitted the money-changers and the oxen into the Temple. They cared not with what corruption they filled Gods houſe, ſo that they might thereby fill their owne houſes and purſes. But this is moſt cleare in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Synagogue, which hath hewne out the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall pillars of her ſuperſtition out of this rocke of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes. Purgatory, Iubilees, Indulgences, all theſe came out of <hi>Iudas</hi> his bag, all coffer and kitchin do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16720:13"/> The doctrine of the Church treaſure in the merits of ſupererogating Saints, a meere deuice to bring treaſure into their Church. Maſſes for the dead, an inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to bring in maſſes of wealth to the liuing. Praying for the dead a very tricke to prey vpon the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. And what turned the <hi>keyes</hi> of the Church into picklockes, or picke-purſes rather, but their abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble couetouſneſſe? Egges of the ſame cockatrice, brats of the ſame hag, are ſteeple and temple broke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, abſolution for ſolutions, impropriations, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound reading ſtipendaries that haue leſſe learning then they haue liuing, ſacrilegious detention, and fraudulent purloyning of the Church ſalary. Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe brought in, and couetouſneſſe holds in theſe plague-ſores and botches of the Church.</p>
            <p>It was not for nothing therefore that when the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell would haue wrought our Sauiour to idolatrie, that he firſt of all laboured to poyſon him with coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, thinking to make couetouſneſſe his ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inghorne to idolatrie. He takes him vp into an high mountaine, from thence ſheweth him all the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the world with the glory of them, &amp; all theſe will he giue him if he will fall down and worſhip him. The diuell knowes it is eaſie to draw on an heart cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with couetouſnes, to the moſt corrupt worſhip that may be. And though the diuel ſped not with our Sauiour, yet with <hi>Demas</hi> he did, who, if <hi>Dorotheus</hi> be <note place="margin">Doroth. de vitis, &amp;c.</note> of any credit, turned from the faith of Chriſt to be an <hi>Idoll Prieſt of Theſſalonica.</hi> A foule, a fearefull fall. But whence might he take it? <hi>Paul</hi> tels vs, 2. Tim. 4. 10. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas hath forſaken me, and hath embraced this preſent world.</hi> How eaſie is it to make him the <hi>diuels Prieſt,</hi> that is once <hi>Mammons Chaplaine?</hi> What religion or
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16720:13"/> falſe worſhip will not that man embrace, that hath once embraced this world? The world is like the whores of <hi>Midian,</hi> with whom no ſooner an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> can be familiar, but he ſhall be entiſed to the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the dead, to the ſacrifices of <hi>Baal-Peor.</hi> To mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the <hi>daughter of a ſtrange god</hi> is a groſſe tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Law. And yet how many ſticke not to wed to the Canaanites, &amp; ſo get not thornes in their ſides, but in their conſciences, and all becauſe their hearts are firſt wedded to the world?</p>
            <p>3 Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine.</hi> Alas, the couetous man thinkes this a very vaine Commandement. Now fie vpon ſuch preciſeneſſe. What! may not a man for his aduantage, to put off his commodity, helpe him ſelfe now and then with an oath? He thinketh this needleſſe ſcupuloſitie. Nay and yet behold a worſe abomination then this. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth couetouſneſſe, <hi>coloured couetouſneſſe,</hi> or the <hi>cloke of couetouſneſſe,</hi> 1. Theſſ. 2. 5. Now though in the former Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſticketh not for gaine to corrupt religion, yet here for aduantage it will paint with religion, and put on a religious cloke or habite. Thus did the couetous Phariſes prophane Gods holy name, while they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured widdowes houſes vnder the <hi>colour of long prayer,</hi> Math. 23. 14. There was couetouſneſſe <hi>colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> with religion. Certainly Gods holy name is not more abuſed by profane couetouſneſſe, when it muſt be made a broker to helpe off baſe commodities, then it is by ſeeming-religious couetouſneſſe, when men vſe religion for a ſiluer hook, &amp; profeſſe it as the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemites receiued circumciſion, Gen. 34. 23. <hi>Shall not their flockes, and their ſubſtance, and all their cattell be</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16720:14"/> 
               <hi>ours?</hi> So, ſhall not their cuſtome and their counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance be ours? Onely let vs make a ſhew of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, for this is a maine principle in a couetous mans Catechiſme, that <hi>gaine is godlineſſe,</hi> 1. Tim. 6. 5. and therefore cares not to make a ſhew of <hi>godlineſſe</hi> to bring in <hi>gaine:</hi> that ſo in a profane ſence he may ſay with himſelfe, <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> (pretended) <hi>is great gaine.</hi> But ſuch with the Phariſes ſhall receiue the greater damnation.</p>
            <p>4. Commandement, <hi>Remember thou keepe holy the Sabboth day.</hi> The couetous man is of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. He thinkes religion maketh men idle. <hi>The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are idle, therefore they crie, Let vs go ſacrifice,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> Exod. 5. The couetous man thinketh the <hi>reſt</hi> of the Sabboth to be but idleneſſe. It is a day loſt in a weeke, ſeuen weekes and an halfe in a yeare. Oh how it grudges the wretch to ſpare God ſo much time! Therefore they crie, Amos 8. 5. <hi>When will the Sabboth be gone that we may ſell corne?</hi> Nay he hath not the patience now to ſtay ſo long. He cries not now, When will the <hi>Sabboth,</hi> but when will the <hi>Sermon</hi> be done? Couetouſneſſe was modeſt in <hi>Amos</hi> his dayes, it would then ſtay marketting till the Sabboth were done. It is now growne more profligate and impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and dares impropriate as Gods <hi>tenthes</hi> in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, ſo Gods <hi>ſeauenths</hi> in the fourth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. What makes many keepe their Sabboths in their ſaddles, and not ſo much as to keepe <hi>Sabbatum aſinorum</hi> in the bare reſt from labour, but their coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe? What is the reaſon that many Lawyers chambers are in Sabboth afternoones better filled with Clients, then many countrie Churches are with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16720:14"/> people, but couetouſneſſe? This, this is that ſinne that turneth Gods Sabboths into <hi>Sabbatum Tyri,</hi> the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both of Tyrus, Nehe. 13. 16. that brought fiſh and all wares, <hi>and ſold on the Sabboth.</hi> Ieruſalem was troubled with fiſh-merchants on the Sabboth. And many townes and cities in this kingdome are troubled with fleſh-merchants, wine-merchants, ale and beere-mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, cup and tap-merchants; and what breedeth theſe trouble-townes but couetouſneſſe? <hi>He that is greedie of gaine troubles</hi> not onely his <hi>owne houſe,</hi> but a whole towne, a whole citie. And was it better in this your honourable Citie till your worthy <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> oppoſed theſe Tyrian Sabbatarians, &amp; ſet themſelues religiouſly and zealouſly to the ſuppreſſion of Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſolemne ſeruice in the publike ſhambles, and priuate temples of <hi>Bacchus?</hi> Now honoured be their memories that firſt begun that good worke, and no leſſe theirs that do and ſhall continue it. What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter honour can this renowned See, and famous Citie haue, then in their ioynt care and zeale to preſerue Gods holy Sabboths from thoſe foule profanations which couetouſneſſe and the loue of filthy lucre hath inuented? Thoſe Iewes, Amos 8. cryed, When will the <hi>Sabboth be gone that we may ſell?</hi> there was ſome kinde of honeſty yet in their couetouſneſſe. But there is a broode now that crie, When will the Sabboth come, that we may ſell ale, beere, and tipling commodities? They long for the Sabboth, not that they might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy God in the publike aſſemblies of his Saints, but that the ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> may haue their aſſemblies, and guzzeling Randevous in their houſes and cellars. Now compare the ſinne of <hi>Amos</hi> his times with the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16720:15"/> ſinne of ours, and it is but light in compariſon of ours. They broke the Sabboth but in thought and deſire, in word at moſt; but our men groſly profane it by making it both <hi>Sabbatum Tyri,</hi> and <hi>Sabbatum Bacchi</hi> at once, a marketting and a iunketting, a ſelling and a ſwilling day both. And yet as light as their ſin was, ſee what an heauie threatning is denounced againſt them, Am. 8. 8. <hi>Shall not the land tremble for this, and euery one mourne that dwells therein?</hi> And ſhall the land tremble for the lighter, and not much more for the heauier ſinne? How great cauſe haue we to beg of God to giue all ſuch whom it concerneth (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gouernours of the Church, or commonwealth) zeale and reſolution to maintaine Gods honour in this point? that in ſtead of <hi>trembling</hi> and <hi>mourning</hi> there may be ioy and reioycing to all good hearts in the flouriſhing of Gods ordinances. Let me adde one thing that may adde encourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to this work. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> after the report of his care for the Sabboths reformation, prayeth on this maner, verſe 22. <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber me ô God concerning this.</hi> Lay <hi>Nehemiahs Memento</hi> to Gods <hi>Memento,</hi> lay Gods commandement &amp; <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiahs</hi> prayer together: <hi>Remember</hi> thou keepe holy the Sabboth, ſaith God; <hi>Nehemiah</hi> remembers it, and then prayeth, <hi>Remember</hi> me ô God. They with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and confidence may pray to God to <hi>Remember</hi> them, who with courage and conſcience <hi>Remember</hi> him and his Sabboths. But if we <hi>forget</hi> his Sabboths, then <hi>God hath ſworne by the excellencie of Iaacob, Surely he will neuer</hi> forget <hi>any of theſe workes,</hi> Amos 8. 7.</p>
            <p>5. Commandement, <hi>Honour thy father and thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> That which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh of <hi>Leui</hi> in a good
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16720:15"/> ſence, Deut. 33. 9. <hi>He ſaid to his father and mother, I haue not ſeene him,</hi> may be ſaid of him in an ill ſence: He hath an euill, a blinde eye, that will not ſee, and a deafe eare that will not heare, when parents neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties craue reliefe and ſuccour. He thinketh it <hi>no tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion to rob father and mother,</hi> Pro. 28. 24. Nay, he thinketh it no tranſgreſſion to ſterue father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It was the Phariſes diuinitie, Matth. 15. 4. 5. 6. It was no matter how empty the parents bellies were, ſo their <hi>Corban</hi> were filled. As if ſo be the ſmell and ſmoke of the ſacrifice were ſufficient to fat them. This ſinne was before noted to be a ſigne of a reprobate ſence, Rom. 1. 29. and well it may, for verſe 30. ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſigne is, <hi>Without naturall affection.</hi> Euen this ſinne ſtupifies the bowels of nature, and maketh men deny that debt which God, and euen corrupt nature doth call for. This is that ſinne that made the heathen long ſince complaine of thoſe vngracious births that <note place="margin">Filius ante diem patrios inquirit in annos. <hi>Ouid.</hi>
               </note> thought their liues too long from whom they had their liues. <hi>Oh,</hi> ſaith good <hi>Abraham, that Iſmael might liue in thy ſight.</hi> But many a couetous <hi>Iſmael</hi> ſpeaketh like a profane <hi>Eſau,</hi> Oh that the dayes of my fathers mourning were come; not that he would mourne, but onely as heires vſe to do whoſe teares we <note place="margin">Haeredis lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae.</note> know are growne prouerbiall.</p>
            <p>6. Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi> But coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe is a cut-throate, a bloud-ſucking horſeleech. To that height often groweth the thirſt after gold, that it maketh men thirſt after bloud. One of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets calleth Babel, <hi>gold-thirſtie Babel.</hi> And all that know <hi>Babel,</hi> know her to haue bene no leſſe <hi>blood-thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi> then <hi>gold-thirſty.</hi> Yea ſhe is taxed for both, Hab. 2.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16720:16"/> 8. 9. This <hi>Salomon</hi> noteth, Pro. 1. 11. 12. 13. <hi>Come with vs, we will lay waite for bloud, and lie priuily for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent without a cauſe, we will ſwallow them vp aliue like a graue, euen whole as thoſe that go downe into the pit; we ſhall finde all precious riches and fill our houſes with ſpoile.</hi> And verſe 19. <hi>Such are the wayes of euery one that is greedie of gaine, he would take away the life of the owners thereof.</hi> Therefore, Ezek. 22. 13. <hi>Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>bloud</hi> are ioyned together. <hi>Ahab</hi> will haue <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard, or he will haue his bloud. <hi>Iudas</hi> was both <hi>couetous</hi> and a <hi>murtherer,</hi> and therefore a <hi>murtherer</hi> becauſe <hi>couetous.</hi> He ſold not his maiſter ſo much out of an hatred of him, as originally out of the loue of the thirtie peeces. Couetouſneſſe is a bloudy ſinne, and if the hands be not defiled with bloud, it is the law and not conſcience that keepeth them cleane.</p>
            <p>7. Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie.</hi> What licenſeth the publicke ſtewes at <hi>Rome,</hi> and thoſe ſtyes of Curtezans but the Popes <hi>Corban,</hi> and the huge reuenew of crownes they bring to the Popes purſe? It is the inordinate deſire after gaine that foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that beſtiall abomination of brothelry. It is not ſo much the luſt of the fleſh, as the luſt of the eyes, that cauſeth ſuch to be giuen ouer to that brutiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. How many violate their matrimoniall faith and chaſtitie, and the couenant of their God, allured more with the adulterers purſe, then with his perſon? How many a chaſt <hi>Danaë</hi> admitteth an adulterous <hi>Iupiter</hi> deſcending in a golden ſhowre? How many vnchaſt perſons force themſelues to a ſingle life meerly to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the charges of married condition, and lie
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16720:16"/> frying in the flames of their owne ſcorching concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, and ſo do offer vp themſelues vnto <hi>Moloch,</hi> in the fire of their burning luſts?</p>
            <p>8. Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</hi> But as the world hath ſtolen his heart from God, ſo ſticks he not to ſteale from men. This Commandement makes him an arrant theefe. <hi>Iudas</hi> is called a <hi>theefe,</hi> Ioh. 12 6. and why a <hi>theefe,</hi> but becauſe he was <hi>coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous?</hi> Therefore our Sauiour (Mark. 7. 22.) ioynes <hi>thefts</hi> and <hi>couetouſnes;</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. Cor. 6. 10. ioynes <hi>theeues</hi> and <hi>couetous</hi> perſons together, as neare and neighbouring ſinners. <hi>Falſe dealing,</hi> it is a breach of this commandement, it is a fruite of this ſin. Ier. 6. 13. <hi>Euery one is giuen to couetouſnes: they all deale falſly. Oppreſſion,</hi> it is a breach of this commandement, it is a fruite of this ſin. Prou. 28. 16. <hi>A Prince deſtitute of vnderſtanding is a great</hi> oppreſſor, <hi>but he that</hi> hates couetouſneſſe <hi>ſhall prolong his dayes.</hi> See how <hi>oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> and the <hi>hatred of couetouſneſſe</hi> are oppoſed.</p>
            <p>We haue here a whole crowd of abominations all forbidden in this law, as defrauding, ouerreaching, coſining one another in mutuall commerce, in buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling, extortion, incloſures, depopulations, ſacriledge, impropriations, detention of the labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers wages, engroſſers, corne-hoorders, thoſe <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catores humanarum calamitatum,</hi> together with that foule-fangd ſin of vſury, that indeed now bites no longer, but is turned <hi>Euening wolfe,</hi> that ſwalloweth the bones, and leaues not till the morrow. And whence, thinke ye, come theſe litters of ſnakes and vipers? Lo, this is the dunghill in which they breed: A couetous heart is the wombe that conceiues
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16720:17"/> them, the mother that giues breath and being to them all.</p>
            <p>9. Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt thy neighbour.</hi> But as in the former he ſcrupled not at <hi>falſe dealing,</hi> ſo neither in this ſtickes he at <hi>falſe accuſing.</hi> Therfore Luk. 3. <hi>Iohn</hi> ioynes theſe two together, <hi>Accuſe no man falſly, and be content with your wages.</hi> Not to be content, is a fruite of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe; and he that is couetouſly inclined, will not ſticke, in hope of gaine, to ſtraine ſo farre as a falſe accuſation comes to. <hi>Flatterers</hi> they ſin againſt this commandement, and couetouſneſſe teacheth men to flatter. Iude 16. <hi>Whoſe mouthes ſpeake proud things, hauing mens perſons in admiration for aduantage.</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe makes men flatter in hope of gaine, as dogs fawne for cruſts. Knights of the Poſt with their hackney conſciences, what breeds thoſe helliſh mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters but this monſter of couetouſneſſe? What makes many Lawyers make ſo little conſcience of pleading for a naughtie, or againſt a good cauſe, manifeſt tranſgreſſions of this law, but becauſe they ſee their Clients come to them, as <hi>Balaks</hi> meſſengers to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam,</hi> with the <hi>reward of diuination in their hands?</hi> The <hi>deceit of Balaams wages</hi> makes them they care not to what <hi>Balak</hi> they do retaine.</p>
            <p>10. Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe,</hi> &amp;c. What may a man haue that he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uets not? Were his hands as nimble as his thoughts, he muſt liue like another <hi>Adam</hi> in the world by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, no man neare him, no man with him. He hath a chymicall heart of his owne. In his wiſhes he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all into gold. He wiſheth the whole earth had
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16720:17"/> bene mines and Indies. He cannot looke vpon hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <note place="margin">Non aſpicit coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum tanquam coelum, ſed om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia putat eſſe pecunias. <hi>Chryſ. ad</hi> 1. <hi>Cor. hom.</hi> 9.</note> which yet one would thinke might put him by his earthly thoughts, but with a wiſh it were gold too. He is iuſt like the Cardinals of Pope <hi>Benedict</hi> the 12. who being thereunto moued, refuſed to make more Cardinals, vnleſſe he could withall make another world; for this was ſcarce ſufficient (ſaid he) for his Cardinals in preſent being. He could find in his heart with <hi>Alexander</hi> to weepe heartily that there are not, and that he enioyes not more worlds.</p>
            <p>But eſpecially if we take the <hi>affirmatiue</hi> of this commandement as ſome, to be Contentment with a mans condition, then is there no man a more direct tranſgreſſor then is the couetous, who out of a diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with his owne eſtate as not ſufficient, enlargeth his deſires as hell, to couet his neighbours houſe, oxe, aſſe, ſeruant, ſubſtance, goods, lands, or whatſoeuer elſe is his.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee the firſt part of this <hi>danger,</hi> and haue found the couetous a tranſgreſſor of euery of Gods lawes. Go now, go ſilly ſoules, and fondly bleſſe your ſelues, and thinke your caſe good becauſe you are free from the blacke crimes and foule ſinnes of the world, and that you haue no other ſinne, you hope, but onely you are a little couetous. None other? Thou needeſt not, that art guiltie of it. This is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary of all ſins, this breakes all Gods lawes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There is no villanie, no impietie, no iniquitie to which this may not diſpoſe thine heart and hand. It is eaſie to make a couetous man an Atheiſt, a Papiſt, a periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, a profaner of Gods Sabboths, an iron-boweld wretch, a murtherer, an adulterer, a theefe, a falſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16720:18"/> witneſſe, or whatſoeuer elſe the diuell will.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond <hi>danger</hi> followes, and that is in the <hi>puniſhments</hi> which it brings.</p>
            <p>Heauie and wofull are thoſe iudgements which Gods threatens againſt this ſinne. <hi>Wo vnto them that ioyne houſe vnto houſe,</hi> Iſa. 5. 8. <hi>We vnto him that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes that which is not his,</hi> Hab. 2. 6. <hi>Wo vnto him that couets an euill couetouſneſſe vnto his houſe,</hi> Hab. 2. 9. See how God thunders out woes thicke and three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold againſt this ſin. Indeed <hi>the couetous bleſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> Pſal. 10. 3. but in the ſame Pſalme and verſe, <hi>the Lord abhorres him.</hi> Yea he ſo abhorres him, that he euen ſmites his hands at him, Ezek. 22. 13. <hi>I haue ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mine hands at thy diſhoneſt gaine.</hi> Yea he ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres him, that he not onely ſmites his hands at him, but ſmites at him with his hands, Iſa. 57. 17. <hi>For his wicked couetouſneſſe I am angry with him, and haue ſmitten him.</hi> But ſee we a little in particular what thoſe puniſhments are wherewith God ſmites him.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God often ſmites him in his <hi>body.</hi> That hunger, and hardſhip, and reſtleſneſſe wherewith he wearies and weares out his poore carkaſſe, is but a whip of his owne making, but God alſo laſhes and ſcourges him with his ſcorpions: Iob 20. 20. <hi>Surely he ſhall find no quietneſſe in his belly.</hi> What got <hi>Gehezi</hi> by his rich bootie? The plague of leproſie vpon his bodie, 2. Kin. 5. 27. What got <hi>Achan</hi> by his great prize? A great heape of ſtones vpon his bodie, Ioſh. 7. 26. So <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> got a ſword in his bowels, and <hi>Iudas</hi> an halter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his necke, the gaines of many a corne-hoorder, and the iuſt end of many a wretched oppreſſor. And what got <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> by their proiect, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16720:18"/> a miſerable and ſudden end? <hi>He that hates couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſhall prolong his dayes,</hi> Prou. 28. 16. but theſe had their dayes ſhortened for this ſinne. Many a faire day might they haue liued, if they had kept themſelues free from this foule ſinne. Now let <hi>Iudas</hi> while he ſwings in his halter, boaſt of his thirtie peeces. Now let <hi>Balaam</hi> boaſt of his wages. The reward of diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ſweete in his eye, but let him tell vs how ſweete is the Iſraelites ſword in his bowels. Now <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hezi</hi> go bleſſe thy ſelfe with thy talent of ſiluer, and thy two changes of raiment, but yet tell vs whether is better the body or raiment? So iuſt it is, that he that will couet <hi>Naamans</hi> ſiluer, <hi>Naamans</hi> raiment, ſhould be clothed, ſhould be plagued with <hi>Naamans</hi> le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God ſmites him in his <hi>goods.</hi> And that which is his god, his heauen, his happineſſe, God makes a curſe, a croſſe, a plague vnto him. God plagues him in his goods, either in denying him the vſe, or in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing him of the poſſeſſion of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In denying him the vſe of them, Eccleſ. 6. 2. <hi>God giues him not power to eate thereof.</hi> All the vſe he hath of his riches, is but <hi>to behold them with his eyes,</hi> Eccl. 5. 10. The plague of the Prince of Samaria is vpon him, who ſaw great plentie and abundance, but might not taſte of it. All the good he hath of his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, is but for his eye. His backe and his belly are oft in his greateſt abundance pinched and pined; and that pleaſure which his eye hath, is but a miſerable pleaſure too; for the <hi>eye is not ſatisfied with ſiluer,</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. 4. 8. They are but <hi>Homines ad metalla damnati,</hi> no better then the miſerable Indians, worne out in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16720:19"/> mines vnder Spaniſh tyranny. Their drinke increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <note place="margin">Et maior acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio fit ei ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior acceſſio paupertatis. Na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quo plura ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſerit, eo plura concupiſcit. Quo ergo plura contupiſcit, eo magis fit pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Qui enim plura concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit pauperior eſt. Quum ergo centum talenta habeat non eſt valde mendicus, mille enim cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. Quum aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mille acceperit tum magis fit pauper. Non amplius mille vt prius, ſed decem millium ſe dicit egere. vide plura <hi>Chryſ. ad</hi> 1. <hi>Cor. hom.</hi> 14. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Chryſoſt. ad</hi> 1. <hi>Cor. hom.</hi> 15 Etiam ſi cellae penatiae impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fueris clauem, ſi oſtium, ſi ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctem, fruſtra fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis omnia qui auaritiam peſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum latronem intus incluſeris, &amp; qui poteſt omnia expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are. <hi>Id, ibid.</hi>
               </note> their thirſt, their riches their pouertie, their abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance their want. Iob 20. 22. <hi>In the fulneſſe of his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie he ſhall be in ſtraits,</hi> euen in ſtraits of want in the midſt of his fulneſſe. And herein is the couetous the moſt miſerable of ſinners. For other ſinners yet, though they loſe the pleaſures of the life to come, yet do they enioy ſome kind of pleaſure in this life: but the couetous, as God will depriue him of the future, ſo he depriues himſelfe of the preſent world, and ſo enioyes neither.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But it may be, the foole thinkes this no miſery; God therefore depriues him of the poſſeſſion, and ſtrips him cleane of all his goods. God hath a <hi>worme</hi> to ſmite their <hi>gourds,</hi> he hath <hi>vermine</hi> to conſume their <hi>Manna</hi> gathered and hoorded vp againſt his commandement. This ſin leaues a mans whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with Gods curſe, which ſhall make his bagges like his deſires, bottomleſſe, and ſo ſhall all run out. Iob 20. 20. 21. <hi>He ſhall not ſaue of that which he deſired, there ſhall none of his meate be left, therefore ſhall no man looke for his goods.</hi> The couetous man hath many a one that gapes after his goods, but God often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues and diſappoints them all; his goods are often gone before himſelfe. <hi>He hath ſwallowed downe riches, he ſhall vomite them vp againe, God ſhall cast them out of his belly,</hi> Iob 20. 15. Greedy gourmandizing tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chermen, that ſwallow their meate downe whole, and as neuer knowing when they haue enough, do ſtill lay in and lay on, do ſo oppreſſe their ſtomackes, that nature is faine to ſeeke its owne eaſe by vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. When men will be rich, and cannot waite Gods
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:16720:19"/> leiſurely diſtribution, and neuer know when they haue enough, but with <hi>Behemoth</hi> thinke to draw vp all <hi>Iordan</hi> into their iawes; they do ſo oppreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that God giueth their eſtate a vomit, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth theſe greedy guts to regurgitate thoſe morſels ſo rauenouſly deuoured. Excellent is that place, Ier. 17. 11. <hi>He ſhall leaue his riches in the middest of his dayes.</hi> It is an hell to him to leaue his riches in the end of his dayes, but God will bring him early to his hell, <hi>He ſhall leaue them in the middeſt of his dayes.</hi> But what ſhall become of him then in the end of his dayes? The words following tell vs, <hi>And at his end he ſhall be a foole.</hi> God will make him a poore man, and a foole both. He ſhall loſe both his wealth and his wits; for whoſe wits would not cracke to loſe his god? God is iuſt, and therefore maketh them a prey vnto others who haue preyed vpon others. See Hab. 2. 6. 7. 8. <hi>Wo vnto him that increaſeth that which is not his: how long? and to him that loadeth himſelfe with thicke clay. Shall they not riſe vp ſuddenly that ſhall bite thee? and awake that ſhall vexe thee? and thou ſhalt be their prey. Becauſe thou haſt ſpoyled many nations, all the remnant of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall ſpoyle thee.</hi> God will ſpoyle theſe ſpoylers, and he which hath bene <hi>praedo minoris,</hi> ſhall himſelfe be <hi>praeda maioris,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh. <note place="margin">In Pſal. 38.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. God ſmiteth him in his <hi>poſterity</hi> and <hi>children.</hi> He cares not to depriue himſelfe of an inheritance in heauen, and all to leaue his children an inheritance on earth. What maketh him lay about him? what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him thus take on? He is deſirous to raiſe his houſe, to make his children gentlemen, men of place and regard. But alas he deceiueth himſelfe, and the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16720:20"/> iſſue befooleth him. As the father was a rich begger, ſo the children proue poore gentlemen. Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe raiſeth not, but ruines houſes, Hab. 2. 9. 10. <hi>Wo vnto him that couets an euill couetouſneſſe to his houſe.</hi> For he that is <hi>greedy of gaine</hi> raiſeth not, but <hi>troubleth his houſe.</hi> He coueteth an euill couetouſneſſe to his houſe, that is, by his couetouſneſſe he bringeth euill vpon his houſe. But what euill? verſe 10. <hi>Thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted ſhame to thine owne houſe;</hi> not honor, not great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but <hi>ſhame,</hi> euen the ſhame of beggery, and the ſhame of ruine, and a diſhonourable downfall. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe leaueth the children heires of a curſe as well as of goods, for his goods are an <hi>execrable thing,</hi> accurſed goods. The leproſie of <hi>Naaman</hi> claue not onely to <hi>Gehezi,</hi> but to him <hi>and to his ſeed for euer,</hi> 2. King. 3. 27. What got <hi>Gehezies</hi> ſeed and poſterity by their fathers couetouſneſſe? What other heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they got I wot not, ſure I am they got a filthy hereditary leproſie. For <hi>Gehezies</hi> couetouſneſſe is his ſeed plagued with leproſie. For many a couetous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſinne is his poſterity plagued with beggery. <hi>He hath not power to eate</hi> of his owne goods, Eccl. 6. 2. I but the more he ſpareth, the more his child heires. So would one thinke indeed, but yet it proues otherwiſe; for not his childe, <hi>but a ſtranger eateth thereof.</hi> I but what becomes of his children then? Either taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>with fiſh-hookes,</hi> Amos 4. 2. a fit plague for the fathers ſinne; or elſe, Iob 20. 10. <hi>His children ſhall flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the poore.</hi> See what his gentlemen come to. To that miſerable baſe beggery ſhall they come, that they ſhall be glad to flatter a meane man for an almes, and faune vpon a poore man for a cruſt. How ordinarily
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16720:20"/> is prodigality heire to couetouſneſſe? and the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall heire ſcattering that in a few dayes that the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous father was gathering many yeares, how quickly is he brought to the trough? how ſoone brought to flatter and faune for huskes and hogs meate? Oh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this you that colour this iniquity with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion <note place="margin">Noli parcere theſauris cadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, theſauris va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. Noli ſub imagine pietatis augere pecunia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Filijs inquis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is ſeruo. Pallia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſe volunt, &amp; dealbare vt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi propter filios videantur ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re homines quod propter auaritiam ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant. <hi>Auguſt. de dec. Chord. c.</hi> 12. Filijs meis ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo. Haec eſt vox pietatis, excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio iniquitatis. Id. in Pſal. 38. Habeo filios quibus labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt hoc filios amare ſed porius necare. Nolo te talem patrem ſentiant filij tui, nolo ſic prouideas. Id. hom. 48.</note> of honeſt care for your children, I intreate you as <hi>Iob</hi> did his wife, Iob 19. 17. euen <hi>for the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens ſake of your owne bodies</hi> to take heed and beware of couetouſneſſe. As you feare the leproſie of Gods curſe, and the canker of his vengeance vpon your children, ſo take heede of leauing them heires of ſuch goods as couetouſneſſe hath ſcraped together. Leaue them heires of ſuch goods as withall they may be heires of Gods bleſſing. Take heed of tranſmitting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to them ſuch a cankred inheritance as may diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit them of all. Were it not that couetouſneſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth men without naturall affection, I ſhould hope this argument might preuaile.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But yet the worſt <hi>danger</hi> of all is yet behind. If God in his patience do forbeare in theſe, yet in the fourth place without faile will God plague him in his <hi>ſoule.</hi> It is a ſoule-plaguing ſinne, not onely in regard of the inward tortures and cares wherewithall his ſoule is ſo diſtracted, that <hi>the abundance of the rich will not ſuffer him to ſleepe,</hi> Eccl. 5. 12: Nor yet in regard of the continuall torment his inſatiable deſires put him to, whereby he is like a man ſicke of the dogged appetite, euer in hunger and thirſt without ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; and his vexation little eaſier then the rich glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons in hell; who was euer in a burning deſire after that drop of water which ſhould neuer be granted
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16720:21"/> him. Not onely in theſe, but in a farre worſe reſpect is it a ſoule-plaguing ſinne, in that it excludeth the ſoule from God and heauen. Hab. 2. 10. <hi>Thou haſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt thine owne ſoule.</hi> Wherein? In diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it of heauen. Epheſ. 5. 5. <hi>The couetous man hath no inheritance in the kingdome of Chriſt, and of God.</hi> He that is thus greedie of inheritance on earth, yet loſeth all <note place="margin">Vis eſſe haeres terrae, ſed non habes in coelo haereditatem. Studium ponis vt alijs relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quas haeredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, teipſum autem priues? <hi>Chryſoſt. ad Eph. hom.</hi> 18.</note> inheritance in heauen. 1. Cor. 6. 9. 10. <hi>Know ye not that the vnrighteous ſhall not inherit the kingdome?</hi> Be not deceiued; <hi>neither theeues, nor couetous ſhall inherit the kingdome of God.</hi> Indeed the couetous bleſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, Pſal. 10. 3. and with no leſſe then the hopes of heauen, but <hi>he is deceiued. For what is the hope of the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite though he hath gained, when God takes away his ſoule?</hi> Iob 27. 8. How ſhould this awaken men <hi>to take heed and beware?</hi> What though thou gaine the whole world by thy couetous courſes, yet what ſhall it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage thee <hi>to gaine the whole world, and to loſe thine owne ſoule?</hi> He that purchaſeth the whole world with the price and loſſe of his ſoule, will find but a biting &amp; a ſmarting bargaine of it. He muſt needs be a loſer by the bargaine, for he loſeth God, heauen, happineſſe, his ſoule and himſelfe. Among all thy gaines thou art ſure to haue hell into the bargaine. What euer thou gaineſt, Satan will be ſure to gaine thy foule.</p>
            <p>Now then, ô thou couetous man, be pleaſed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to looke ouer theſe Items, and ſumme vp thy gaines. <hi>Auarus ſemper in rationibus:</hi> A couetous man is much in his counting houſe. Among other thine accounts be ſo good as to looke ouer this. <hi>Inprimis</hi> by thine oppreſſion, fraudulent and falſe dealing, thou haſt gotten ſo many pounds. <hi>Item</hi> by thine vſury and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16720:21"/> extortion ſo many hundreds. <hi>Item</hi> by thy bribery ſo many thouſands. Well, what is the whole ſumme? The totall ſumme is, the curſe of God vpon thy <hi>body,</hi> the curſe of God vpon thy <hi>goods,</hi> the curſe of God vpon thy <hi>children,</hi> the curſe of Gods eternall vengeance vpon thy <hi>ſoule.</hi> Now in good ſooth, and are not theſe goodly gaines? would they not ſet any mans teeth on watering? Yea but it may be theſe are but idle ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crowes, the figments of Preachers idle braines. No, no. God hath ſworne twice in one prophecy, Amos 4. 2. Amos 8. 7. to make them good. God can no more be forſworne then he can ceaſſe to be God. If he do forbeare the infliction of the temporall plagues, yet ſhall it be abundantly recompenced in the heauy weight of eternall torment.</p>
            <p>And thus haue we ſeene the double danger of this ſinne, which may both ſerue to verifie the Apoſtles ſaying, 1. Tim. 6. 10. That <hi>the deſire of money is the roote of all euill,</hi> of all euill both of <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>puniſhment;</hi> as alſo to terrifie our dead hearts, and make them awake to <hi>take heed and beware of couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third thing followeth. The <hi>remedies</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiues. What are we the better to know our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and the danger thereof, vnleſſe we know the remedies withall? The <hi>remedies</hi> therefore are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That which we find, 1. Ioh. 5. 4. <hi>This is the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory that ouercometh the world, euen our faith.</hi> Faith o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercometh not onely the feare of the world in threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but the loue of the world in entiſing. The roote of this roote of all euill is commonly diffidence and diſtruſt in Gods all-ſufficient prouidence. This ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16720:22"/> men ſo greedily and eagerly prouide for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, becauſe diſtruſtfully they imagine that they are left to the wide world, as ſhiftleſſe and fatherleſſe children. So much implieth our Sauiours ſpeech, verſe 28. of this Chapter: <hi>How much more will he cloath you ô ye of little faith?</hi> Our <hi>great cares</hi> come from our <hi>little faith.</hi> Greater faith would leſſen our cares. This remedie <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth <hi>Timothie,</hi> 1. Tim. 6. 11. <hi>O man of God flie theſe things,</hi> namely thoſe foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and noyſome luſts which drowne men in deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and perdition riſing from the loue of money. But how may we flie them? <hi>Follow after</hi> righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, godlineſſe, <hi>faith.</hi> The ſoule in which this grace hath reſidence, ſhall find it an heauenly amulet or plague-cake to defend it from the poyſon of this ſinne. For faith not onely <hi>purifies the heart,</hi> and ſo purgeth out this droſſe, but it alſo <hi>ſatisfieth the heart,</hi> by making God its portion whereby the infinite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of the ſoule is filled, which nothing can ſatisfie but the fruition of the infinite God. He alone that filleth heauen and earth and all things therein, he alone can fill the boundleſſe deſires of the ſoule. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faith maketh him ours. And the ſoule hauing made God hers by faith, ſhe ceaſſeth to ſeeke ſatisfaction from the temporall, and finite creatures. Faith is a chymicall grace. As couetouſneſſe is an earthly Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymiſt that turneth <hi>gold</hi> into <hi>God,</hi> ſo is faith a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Chymicke that turneth <hi>God</hi> into <hi>gold, ſiluer,</hi> and whateuer the heart wanteth and deſireth, Iob 22. 23. <note place="margin">Eritue omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potens lectiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum aurum tuum, &amp; argen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vireſue tibi. Sic Iun.</note> 24. 25. <hi>If thou returne to the Almightie, then ſhalt thou lay vp gold as dust, and the gold of Ophir as the ſtones of the brookes, yea the</hi> Almighty <hi>ſhall be thy choyce</hi> gold
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16720:22"/> and ſiluer, <hi>and ſtrength vnto thee.</hi> Would we haue our fill of gold and ſiluer, ſo as we would haue our thirſt quenched? Let vs make God our portion by faith. He that by faith hath made <hi>God</hi> his <hi>gold,</hi> ſhall neuer through couetouſnes made <hi>gold</hi> his <hi>god.</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things can no more fill the heart, then ſpirituall things a cheſt. The world can no more fill the heart, <note place="margin">Mundus circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laris eſt, cor quadratum; cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam implere non poteſt.</note> then a circle can a ſquare. God alone is he that can ſatisfie the ſoule, on whom the ſoule hauing layed hold, it then holds it ſelfe well apaid, and then, and neuer till then ſings with <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſal. 16. 5. 6. <hi>The Lord is the portion of mine inheritance. The lines are fallen to me in pleaſant places, yea I haue a goodly heritage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sobrietie and temperance, ſober affections in the vſe of theſe earthly things. For though couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and prodigalitie be two extremes, yet oftentimes couetouſneſſe is but ſubordinate to prodigalitie; and mens prodigall and intemperate courſes, makes them couetouſly ſcrape that together which may be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable to their luſts. Many haue braue, or baſe minds rather, they muſt flaunt, and cut it out in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, furniture, houſhold, attendance. Pride muſt haue this thing, &amp; delicacie muſt haue that; pleaſure cals for this, and luſt for that. Which inordinacies of theirs being coſtlier then their own eſtates can beare, then couetouſneſſe inſtructs them to lay the burden vpon others. Theſe intemperate affections crying like horſe-leeches <hi>Giue, giue,</hi> they teach couetouſnes to crie <hi>Take, take;</hi> and ſo by iniuſtice, exaction and oppreſſion do ſeeke maintenance and exhibition for their pride and luxury out of other mens eſtates, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:16720:23"/> other mens maintenance which is for their bare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, muſt be rauened vp to ſerue their inordinate and helliſh voluptuouſneſſe. Hence comes it that the poore Tenant is racked to maintaine the Landlords dogs, hawkes, and coaches; the poore Tenants backe ſtripped, that their dead walls may be richly clothed; the poore Tenant can ſcarce go in good ruſſet on high dayes, becauſe the Landlord, like the rich glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, muſt fare deliciouſly, and go in purple euery day. Moderation breeds contentation: contentation pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues from couetouſneſſe. He that is content with his owne, will neuer put forth his hand to wrong an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Set bounds and a ſtint to thine eſtate, and learne to know when thou haſt <hi>enough.</hi> Couetouſnes is a deſire of more then <hi>enough.</hi> Therefore do men ſtill deſire more, becauſe they thinke they haue not yet <hi>enough.</hi> He that would be relieued againſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, muſt firſt ſeeke to ſtint his deſires; a man ſhall neuer ſtint his deſires, till his eſtate be ſtinted. Mens eſtates are not ſo much increaſed by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, as their deſires are made endleſſe by their eſtates boundleſſe. If <hi>Eſau</hi> had bene as honeſt in other things as in this, he ſhould neuer haue deſerued the brand of <hi>a profane perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> As profane as he was, I could wiſh this leſſon were learned of him. As profane as he was, he was an honeſter man in this, then thouſands that now liue. Wil ye heare how like an honeſt man he ſpeakes? Gen. 33. 9. <hi>I haue</hi> enough <hi>my brother, keepe that which thou haſt to thy ſelfe.</hi> Behold how farre he is beyond the honeſtie of the <hi>Harpyes</hi> and cormorants of our times, that neuer knowing when they haue enough,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16720:23"/> are euer fixing their kites clawes and their gryphons talants vpon their poore brother <hi>Iacobs</hi> goods. Foure things are ſpecified, Pro. 30. 15, 16. that neuer ſay, <hi>It is enough:</hi> to which we may adde a fift, namely a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous heart that knoweth no ſtint of its owne deſires and endeuours. The way to preuent this immodera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is to ſee when we are well, when we haue enough. A point being determinable, why make not men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to determine it? God forbids the King, Deut. 17. 16, 17. <hi>to multiply horſes to himſelfe, and greatly to multiply his ſiluer and gold;</hi> and yet who hath greater vſes of, and fairer pretences for theſe things then Princes haue? If a King may not multiply aboue that which is enough for a King, what prerogatiue haue inferiour ſubiects to haue eſtates boundleſſe? We can ſay of others, They haue enough, if they can ſee. If we can ſee when others haue enough, why do we ouerlooke our owne eſtates? This is an <hi>euill coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe,</hi> when men are euer lading themſelues with thicke clay, and haue neither the hearts nor the grace to ſet downe an <hi>Hucuſque</hi> to anſwer Gods <hi>Quouſque,</hi> Hab. 2. 6. an <hi>Hitherto</hi> to Gods <hi>How long.</hi> For this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſin were the Iewes threatned, Iſa. 2. 6. 7. <hi>Therefore thou haſt forſaken thy people, &amp;c. becauſe their land is full of ſiluer and gold, neither is there any end of their treaſures, any end of their chariots.</hi> Enough, we ſay, is as good as a feaſt. And what ſhould a man do fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting or feeding when his belly is full? The purſe muſt know a meaſure as well as the belly. And then it will be as eaſie to fill mens eyes as their bellies. Not that men hauing enough, ſhould giue vp their honeſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and receiue in no more; but hauing enough,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16720:24"/> ſhould lay vp no more, but make the ouerfloate of their cup ſeruiceable to the maintenance of Gods worſhip, and the reliefe of his poore Saints. Take this courſe, and be couetous if thou canſt. <hi>Let your conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation be without couetouſneſſe,</hi> Heb. 13. 5. What helpe may we haue hereunto? <hi>And be content with things preſent.</hi> Contentation preſerueth from couetouſnes. Then, and neuer till then, will a mans heart be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented when he hath enough, and knoweth he hath enough, and is reſolued not to go further then enough.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Free thy ſelfe from a falſe opinion of riches. The conceit which men haue of riches, is falſe. They think riches lieth in <hi>Hauing much.</hi> They are deceiued. <note place="margin">Anim' hominis diues, non arca appellari ſolet, quamuis illa ſit plena, dum te inanem video, diuitem non putabo. <hi>Cicer. Parad.</hi> 6.</note> God is called <hi>Rich</hi> in Scripture, not for <hi>money,</hi> but for <hi>mercie;</hi> not for <hi>hauing goods,</hi> but for <hi>doing good,</hi> Rom 10. 12. <hi>He that is Lord ouer all, is rich vnto all that call vpon him.</hi> Wherein is God rich? Not in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Lord ouer all,</hi> but in <hi>doing good vnto all</hi> that call vpon him. So that I would not forbid men to be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous of riches, ſo they would be couetous of true and <hi>durable riches.</hi> Couet true riches, and ſpare not. Couet to be <hi>Rich in God, Rich in faith, Rich in good works.</hi> The more couetous of theſe riches, the happier is thy ſoule. This was the fooles error next my text, that conceiued Riches to be all in Hauing, and not in Doing good. Therefore it is added in the cloſure of that parable, So is euery one that gathereth riches to himſelfe, and is not rich in God. <hi>So,</hi> that is, as ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a foole as was he.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Climbe vp mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> and from thence take a view of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and little liſt and loue ſhalt thou
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16720:24"/> haue to the wilderneſſe of the world. Get a piercing eye in meditation to ſee the inuiſible God, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and beautie of heauen; and therewithall ſhall we find our affections ſo inflamed, that they ſhall eaſily ſlake and coole in regard of earthly things. Oh ſhame that we that profeſſe the hope of an inheritance with the Saints in light, ſhould lauiſh out ſo much of our precious time, of our precious life, and the ſtrength of our affections in the ſo eager purſuite of the traſh of the earth. View well that heauenly Ieruſalem on high, that <hi>Citie which is of pure gold,</hi> Apoc. 21. 18. whoſe <hi>ſtreete is alſo pure gold,</hi> verſe 21. and in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of that Citie, thou ſhalt ſay of all earthly felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties as <hi>Hiram</hi> ſaid of the cities which <hi>Salomon</hi> gaue him, 1. King. 9. 13. <hi>They pleaſed him not: and he ſaid, What cities are theſe which thou hast giuen me, my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? And he called them,</hi> viz. in indignation, <hi>the land of Cabul vnto this day,</hi> that is, a dirtie, a mirie land. Heauen is our land of Canaan; fixe we our eye and heart thereon, and the earth <hi>will not pleaſe vs,</hi> it will be a very land of <hi>Cabul,</hi> a dirtie, droſſie land in our eie. Oh fond thing for vs that hope for the milke and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of <hi>Canaan,</hi> to long and luſt after the ſtinking garlicke and onions of Aegypt. Oh fond thing for vs that hope for a crowne and kingdome, thus to abaſe our ſelues to lie raking in the kennels of the earth. Thus if men would but ſeriouſly meditate, and work vp their thoughts and hearts to the loue of the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of heauen, it would ſoone breed in them an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglect, if not a contempt of this preſent world. This remedy our Sauiour teacheth, Matth. 6. 19, 20, 21. <hi>Lay not vp treaſures for your ſelues on earth, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:16720:25"/> as if he had ſaid, <hi>Take heed and beware of couetouſnes;</hi> and then followes, <hi>But lay vp treaſures for your ſelues</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Nemo enim poteſt niſi co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitare de the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauro ſuo, &amp; quodam cordis itinere diuitias ſuas ſequi. Et ſicut eccleſiam praeceſſit caput eius, ſic Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anum praecedat cor eius. Eamus ergo hinc ex qua parte poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus, ſequetur totum noſtrum quo praeceſſerit aliquid noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Aug. ſerm. de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ.</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>in heauen;</hi> and then, <hi>Where our treaſure is, there will our heart be.</hi> Our Head is in heauen, what do our hearts on earth then? Let Head and heart be toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The ſame remedy <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth <hi>Timothy</hi> among many others, 1. Tim. 6. 11, 12. <hi>O man of God flie theſe things,</hi> namely the couetous deſires of the world. But how ſhall that be done? <hi>Lay hold of eternall life.</hi> The faſter hold we take of the world to come, the looſer hold ſhall we haue of this world, and the leſſe hold ſhall this world haue of vs. For this makes men hold ſo faſt on, and in this life, becauſe they haue ſo ſlacke an hold of the life to come. This made <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> dwell in tents in the land of promiſe, not raiſing cities or making great buildings, <hi>becauſe he looked for a Citie hauing a foundation whoſe builder and maker was God,</hi> Heb. 11. 9. 10. And thus <hi>Dauid</hi> ſeemeth to weane his heart from the loue of the earth, Pſal. 17. 14. 15: hauing before ſpoken of the men of this world who haue their portion in this life, he ſubioynes, <hi>I will behold thy face in righteouſneſſe, and when I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake I ſhall be ſatisfied with thine image.</hi> As if he had ſaid, I neither enuie nor deſire their happineſſe, my teeth water not after their delicates, I long alone after that ſweet ſatietie which I ſhall haue in the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie of the glorious Trinitie at the day of my bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed reſurrection. And ſo much for the <hi>remedies;</hi> and ſo much for the <hi>obiect</hi> of the caution.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Third point remaines. The <hi>Perſons</hi> warned to beware. <hi>And he ſaid vnto them.</hi> Vnto them? Vnto whom? See the firſt verſe of the Chapter, <hi>There was</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:16720:25"/> 
               <hi>an innumerable multitude of people, in ſo much that they trode one vpon another.</hi> And he ſaid vnto them, euen to this whole and huge multitude, to them all, one and another, <hi>Take ye heed and beware.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Couetouſneſſe is an Epidemicall diſeaſe, an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall plague from which no ſort is free. <hi>He ſaid to them,</hi> euen to them all. Ier. 6. 13. <hi>For from the leaſt of them, euen to the greateſt of them</hi> euery one <hi>is giuen to couetouſneſſe.</hi> There is no ſort or condition of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons free from this peſtilence. Some ſinnes are parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to ſome callings, as to the Miniſtery, to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy alone; ſome peculiar to ſome conditions, as to the rich or to the poore alone: but this poyſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth all ages, callings, conditions, ſexes, perſons. Therefore now Chriſt ſpeakes not as verſe 1. <hi>to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> but preaching againſt couetouſneſſe he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to them all, <hi>He ſaid vnto them, Take heed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.</hi> I conceiue our Sauiours auditory to be much of the nature of this preſent aſſembly; and I conceiue this preſent aſſembly to be a mixt company of all ſorts and conditions: and therefore as <hi>Christ ſaid to them,</hi> ſo I ſay to you, euen to all, and euery of you, <hi>Take heed and beware of couetouſneſſe.</hi> But becauſe hearers commonly are like ouer baſhfull gueſts, that either faſt, or feed not ſo liberally as they ſhould for want of a caruer, giue me leaue therefore to take this office vpon me, and to lay vpon euery mans trencher what may beſt ſuite, though not with his tooth, yet with his neceſſitie.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt, according to the rule of well ordered charity, to begin at home; and as our Sauiour began his ſermon in this Chapter, <hi>He began to ſay to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:16720:26"/> 
               <hi>firſt of all;</hi> and as the Prophet in taxing this ſinne, Ier. 6. 13. to begin with the <hi>Prieſt and the Prophet;</hi> let me aduiſe you of the tribe of <hi>Leui,</hi> who are to teach others the contempt of the world, to take heed of the loue of the world your ſelues. Aboue al men take you heed, and beware you of couetouſneſſe. It is an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularitie, and an offence againſt Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> and Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Canons, 1. Tim. 3. 3. <hi>Not giuen to filthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, not couetous,</hi> and 1. Pet. 5. 2 Not caring for the flocke for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind. Ye are the light and the eyes of the world: If our light proue darkneſſe, how great will that darkneſſe be. This ſinne will put out our eye, and eclipſe our light. Zach. 11. 17. The fooliſh ſheepheards right eye is threatened to be darkened. This is one ſinne that will bring that plague vpon vs. This is a beſotting, blinding, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuating ſinne. Iſay 56. 11. <hi>Theſe greedy dogs can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue enough, and theſe ſheepheards cannot vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, for they all looke to their owne way, euery one for his aduantage, and for his owne purpoſe.</hi> In the verſe before he had complained that they were <hi>dumbe dogs,</hi> that they could not barke. What made them <hi>dumbe dogs?</hi> They were <hi>greedy dogs</hi> that could neuer haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Dogs that are euer feeding and gnawing their bones, haue neither liſt nor leiſure to be bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and keeping the houſe. What was the reaſon theſe ſheepheards could not vnderſtand? They all looked after their owne way, and for their owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage. <hi>Ye cannot ſerue God and Mammon.</hi> They are two contrary Cures ſo infinitely diſtant each from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as no court of Faculties can giue a diſpenſation to ſerue both. We cannot be Gods Miniſters, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:16720:26"/> Mammons chaplaines. I will vſe no other argument to vrge this caution vpon you, then of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,</hi> 1. Tim. 6. 11. <hi>O thou</hi> man of God <hi>flie theſe things.</hi> Which very phraſe ſeemeth to haue a ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment couched vnder it, in that he calleth him the <hi>man of God.</hi> Why ſaith he not as at other times, <hi>ô Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus,</hi> but ô thou <hi>man of God,</hi> but that his calling might be a monitour to him to make him wary and heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? We find mention, Pſal. 17. 14. of the <hi>men of this world,</hi> and Luk. 12. 30. of the <hi>people of this world.</hi> Now this phraſe, <hi>Thou man of God,</hi> me thinkes it ſtandeth in oppoſition vnto thoſe. As if he ſhould haue ſaid, Thou art not a <hi>man of the world,</hi> but <hi>a man of God,</hi> and <hi>ſeekeſt thou great things for thy ſelfe? Seeke them not,</hi> Ier. 45. 5. O man of God flie theſe things, <hi>for after all theſe things ſeeke the people of the world.</hi> Luke 12. 30. It becometh not the <hi>men of God</hi> to be <hi>men of the world.</hi> Indeed, I confeſſe, the <hi>men of the world</hi> haue put an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian tricke vpon <hi>the men of God;</hi> haue taken away, I would but the ſtraw alone, and yet ſtill call for the full tale of bricke both in preaching and hoſpitalitie: and hauing by their ſacriledge made the Miniſterie bare and penurious, and forced many to ſuch ſhifts for their liuelihood as carry an appearance of this ſinne, then they crie vs downe to be inhoſpitall, illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall, and couetous. But yet for all this I could wiſh that the <hi>men of God,</hi> by ioyning not houſe to houſe, but pariſh to pariſh, did not giue the <hi>men of the world</hi> too iuſt cauſe to clamour againſt them for their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe. Pluralities, multitudes of Cures, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of Benefices, Abſence from our flockes for our owne ends and aduantages, Citie Lectures with the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:16720:27"/> neglect of countrey charges, all theſe haue a ſhrewd ſuſpitious appearance of this euill, and maketh the <hi>men of the world</hi> ſpeake broadly, and ſay that none are more couetous then clergie men. Wherefore ô ye <hi>men of God</hi> flie theſe things, <hi>Take heed and beware of couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Ye honourable and reuerend Magiſtrates and Iudges, who are not onely men of God, but vpon whom God hath put his owne name, <hi>I haue ſaid ye are Gods.</hi> Pſal. 82. take ye heed alſo and beware of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe. So <hi>Iethro</hi> would haue <hi>Moſes</hi> his Iudges to be qualified, Exod. 18. 21. <hi>Men fearing God, dealing truly, hating couetouſneſſe.</hi> Theſe are well ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for it is not poſſible they ſhould <hi>deale truly</hi> in the place of iuſtice, that do not <hi>hate couetouſneſſe.</hi> I neither do nor can accuſe any of our reuerend Iudges as guilty of this ſinne, or any ſuch as commonly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it when it ſetteth foote into the iudgment ſeate, ſuch as are iniuſtice, bribery, corruption, rayſing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourites vpon the ruines of honeſt cauſes and men, &amp;c. But onely as one this day in Gods roome, I am bold to beſeech and aduiſe your wiſedomes to <hi>take heed and beware</hi> thereof. And that ſo much the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe this ſinne will make you ſuch as I dare not name. But the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> dares, and doth, <hi>Iſay</hi> 1. 23. <hi>Thy Princes are companions of theeues.</hi> Why ſo? Not for taking of purſes on the high way, but for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king bribes in their chambers: <hi>For euery one loueth gifts, and followeth after rewards; they iudge not the fatherleſſe, neither doth the widowes cauſe come before them.</hi> That is true of the iudgement ſeate, which <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of kingdomes, that <hi>magna regna ſine</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De Ciuit. Dei. l. 4. cap. 4.</note>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:16720:27"/> 
               <hi>iuſtitia,</hi> are but <hi>magna latrocinia.</hi> This ſinne will turne <hi>Guild-hall</hi> into a <hi>Shooters hill,</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter-hall</hi> into a <hi>Sariſ-bury plaine.</hi> Her rulers loue to ſay with ſhame, <hi>Giue ye,</hi> Hoſ. 4. 18. And what difference betweene <hi>giue ye,</hi> and <hi>deliuer ye?</hi> Indeed <hi>giue ye</hi> is not ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous by the law as <hi>deliuer ye;</hi> and <hi>giue ye</hi> goeth oft in chaines of gold, while <hi>deliuer ye</hi> lyeth in fetters of iron: but in the Court of conſcience, &amp; before Gods tribunall, there is no difference betweene <hi>theeuery</hi> and <hi>bribery.</hi> For the ſame commandement that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth theeuery forbiddeth bribery, yea and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it vnder the name of theeuery. That word Hoſ. 4. 18. tranſlated <hi>rulers, Iunius</hi> and the margent of our new Tranſlation reade <hi>ſhields.</hi> Such indeed ſhould men be that are in place of iuſtice; they ſhould be <hi>ſhields</hi> to ſhelter and defend their poore brethren in their right and innocency. But if once theſe <hi>ſhields</hi> ſhall loue and deſire to be gilt, theſe <hi>ſhields</hi> will be turned into ſpoyling ſwords. God ſhield you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye reuerend Iudges from couetouſneſſe. <hi>Walke in iuſtice, ſpeake righteous things, refuſe the gaine of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſay 33.</note> 
               <hi>ſhake your hands from taking of gifts,</hi> ſhake them as <hi>Paul</hi> ſhooke off the viper, thinke them no leſſe dangerous, let them do no more hurt then the viper did him, <hi>ſtop your eares, and ſhut your eyes from ſeeing euill.</hi> There be three ſinnes in Scripture which are called <hi>peccata ingentia,</hi> huge or mighty ſins. You ſhall find them all three together, Amos 5. 12. and the middlemoſt of them is, <hi>They take a bribe;</hi> And well is it placed betweene the other two, as that which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed giueth life to both the other. For why do they <hi>afflict</hi> or oppreſſe <hi>the iuſt? They take a bribe.</hi> And
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16720:28"/> what miſchiefe followeth vpon it? <hi>They turne aſide the poore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the gate</hi> from their right. Take heede of this ſinne as of a <hi>mighty ſinne,</hi> yea as of a burning ſinne that will conſume all, for <hi>fire ſhall conſume the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles of bribery,</hi> Iob 15. 34. Let therefore neither gaine nor rewards be the <hi>remora</hi> to the ſhip of iuſtice, let it ſaile ſpeedily; <hi>Currat lex,</hi> let iuſtice haue a quick courſe. <hi>Iethro</hi> was not pleaſed to ſee cauſes hang from morning to euening, it would haue grudged him farre more to haue ſeene them hang from yeare to yeare: worſt of all it would haue angred him to haue ſeene cauſes vſed as vnconſcionable Chyrurgions vſe ſore legs, hold them long in hand not for the difficulty of, but for the gaine of the cure. Oh that your wiſdomes would thinke of ſome courſe no leſſe for <hi>ſpeede</hi> then integrity in iuſtice, that a good cauſe might not be ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and wearied out with long ſuite, and that a mans right recouered by <hi>law</hi> might not be as coſtly as what is bought by <hi>purchaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. It will not be an vnſeaſonable caueat to all infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Lawyers, to aduiſe them alſo to beware and take heede of couetouſneſſe. I may ſpeake to you as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> with a little change of his words. 1. Cor. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. <hi>Now there is vtterly a fault amongſt you,</hi> euen amongſt you Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, not <hi>becauſe ye go to law one with another,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many of you out of a couetous deſire of gaine, do encourage men that haue bad cauſes to go to law with others. <hi>Why rather ſuffer ye not wrong? why rather ſuſtaine ye not the loſſe</hi> of a little diſhoneſt gaine? <hi>Nay ye your ſelues do wrong, and do harme, and that to your brethren,</hi> whileſt out of a ſquint reſpect to your owne
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:16720:28"/> gaine, you ſticke not to pleade ſuch cauſes as you know to be weake and vniuſt. <hi>Know ye not that the vnrighteous ſhal not inherite the kingdom of God? Be not deceiued. Neither couetous nor extortioners ſhal inherite the kingdom of God.</hi> The Apoſtle addes, <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you.</hi> I would I might not ſpeake in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tenſe, and ſay, And ſuch are ſome of you. I ſpeake not this as if I came hither to maintaine a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh faction between Colledges and Innes of Court; God forbid that we ſhould ſtand vpon this holy ground with ſuch filthy ſhooes; but I ſpeake it out of a deſire of the peace of your owne hearts: to the which I dare referre my ſelfe, and make them the iudges, whether ye be guiltie of this ſinne, yea or no.</p>
            <p>For while with <hi>Abſalom</hi> ye ſay to <hi>euery man,</hi> his cauſe is good, 2. Sam. 15. 3. <hi>See, thy matters</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are good and righteous;</hi> and this, ſaith the text, <hi>he did to euery man,</hi> and ſo ſtole away the hearts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: whileſt, I ſay, with <hi>Abſalom</hi> ye tell euery man, his cauſe is good; and ſo ſteale away, not the <hi>hearts,</hi> for them ye loſe at laſt, but the <hi>goods</hi> of the people, are ye not couetous?</p>
            <p>Whileſt with <hi>Tertullus</hi> for your ſees, you care not to pleade againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> againſt an honeſt mans cauſe, <note place="margin">Clientes ſibi omnes volunt eſſe multos. Bonine an mali ſint, id haud quaeritant. Res magis que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur quàm cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entium Fides, cuiuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di clueat. <hi>Plaut. in Menaec.</hi>
               </note> are ye not couetous?</p>
            <p>Whileſt with the men of <hi>Abiezer,</hi> Iudg. 6. ye will pleade for <hi>Baal,</hi> will for your gaines pleade in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Courts of Iuſtice for baſe debauched adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous drunkards preſented and indicted for their notorious irregularities, and pleade for their honeſtie too; I will not ſay, Are ye your ſelues honeſt? but I dare ſay, Are ye not groſly couetous? Oh take heed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:16720:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:16720:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:16720:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:16720:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:16720:31"/> of this couetouſneſſe; and aboue all fees and incomes in the world, tender your peace with God. In whoſe name and feare, I beſeech you to make a conſcience of pleading euery cauſe. When an ill cauſe cometh to you for counſell, ſay that of it plainly, which the buyer of his commoditie ſpeaketh diſſemblingly, Prou. 20. 14. <hi>It is naught, it is naught.</hi> It is not ſo great a ſinne for a chapman to ſay of a good commoditie, <hi>It is naught, it is naught,</hi> as for a Lawyer to ſay of a naughtie cauſe, <hi>It is good, it is good.</hi> Make a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of pleading againſt a good cauſe. Let not coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe make your wits, skill, learning and tongues, inſtrumentall to iniuſtice. Neither be <hi>Tertulliſts</hi> to pleade againſt <hi>Paul,</hi> nor <hi>Abiezrites</hi> to pleade for <hi>Baal.</hi> Will ye pleade for <hi>Baal?</hi> Let <hi>Baal</hi> and <hi>Belial</hi> pleade for themſelues. How thinke ye to haue the Lord Ieſus for your Aduocate, that dare be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding aduocates for <hi>Baal</hi> and <hi>Belial?</hi> Therefore all Lawyers, <hi>Take heed and beware of couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. I commend this caueat to all Church-patrons: Take ye heed alſo and beware of couetouſneſſe. What is the reaſon that our Church groanes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heauie burden of ſo many inſufficient mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters? Nothing more then the <hi>couetouſnes</hi> of Church-patrons, who while they looke more at the gifts and gratuities in the hand, then gifts and graces of the heart, ſticke not to bring into Gods Sanctuary thoſe for <hi>Leuites</hi> to <hi>diuide the word,</hi> who in good truth, giue them their due, are not worthy the place of <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites</hi> to cleaue and <hi>diuide wood,</hi> and draw water, vnfit for the meaneſt ſeruice of the Sanctuary. Me thinks <hi>Iudas</hi> his halter ſhould make you afraid of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:16720:31"/> his queſtion, <hi>Quid dabitis?</hi> What will ye giue? God gaue him an halter. Take heed leſt while you ask the ſame queſtion, God do not giue you the ſame anſwer. For certainly this ſinne makes you as very theeues as euer was <hi>Iudas:</hi> and what can a theefe looke for, but the halter? You are euery whit as bad as <hi>Iudas.</hi> He ſold the Head, you ſell the members; he the ſhepheard, you the ſheepe; and the ſame ſinne that ſet him, ſets you on worke too, the ſinne of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe. As bad as <hi>Iudas?</hi> Nay in ſome reſpect ye are worſe then he. Not that I am of that heretical opinion of the old <hi>Cainites,</hi> of whom <hi>Auguſtiné</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <note place="margin">Lib. de Haereſ. ad Quodvultd.</note> mention, who held that <hi>Iudas</hi> betrayed Chriſt out of a good and an honeſt mind, as foreſeeing that infinite good which his paſſion &amp; death ſhould bring to mankind. No, I know he was a murtherer and a theefe; and yet I ſay, that you are worſe then he. He ſold but the body, but you ſell ſoules, and ſo make your ſelues guilty of the ſin of that execrable filth of Babylon, whoſe merchandize (Apoc. 18. 13.) is not onely pearles, linnen, ſcarlet, &amp;c. but alſo <hi>the ſoules of men. Iudas</hi> by his barter made but the potters field, you by yours make Chriſts field, Chriſts Church, an <hi>Aceldema,</hi> a field of bloud, while for your wicked pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniary reſpects, in ſtead of <hi>barking dogs</hi> to keepe, you put in rauening wolues and <hi>ſleepie greedy dogs</hi> to kill Chriſts ſheepe. Now as you feare to haue your hands beſmeared with the gore of ſoules, and as you dread that heauie account which muſt be giuen for ſoule-bloud, ſo all Church-patrons <hi>take heed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Me thinkes, in the next place, whileſt this ſinne
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:16720:32"/> is thus complained of, I ſhould heare Landlords, and men that liue on Offices, ſaying to me as the Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans to <hi>Iohn,</hi> Luk, 3. 12. <hi>What ſhall we do?</hi> If couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be thus foule a ſinne, how then, and what then ſhall we do? To whom I giue the ſame anſwer that <hi>Iohn</hi> did to the Publicans and the ſouldiers both, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act no more then is appointed to you,</hi> and <hi>Do no man vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, be content with your wages.</hi> Take heed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of couetouſneſſe, Take heed of exaction, Take heed of oppreſſion, Take heed of racking your rents, Take heed of tentring your poore Tenants. Grinde not the faces of the poore; vncloathe not their loines to cloathe your dead walls. Many Landlords are like <hi>Darius,</hi> Dan. 6. 16. he prayes God to helpe <hi>Daniel,</hi> but in the meane time ſends him to the Lions den: ſo many oppreſſing Landlords, they crie, God helpe, but in the mean time play the Lions. God hath ſworn by his Holineſſe, that he will <hi>takeaway ſuch oppreſſors with thornes,</hi> and their <hi>poſteritie with fiſh-hookes,</hi> Am. 4. 2. God will ſerue them as <hi>Gideon</hi> ſerued the men of <hi>Succoth,</hi> Iudg. 8. 16. whom he did teare with the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and thornes of the wilderneſſe. It is but iuſtice that their fleſh ſhould be torne off with briers, who were thornes and briers to teare off the fleſh of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <note place="margin">Tantum ergo natum eſt vt lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca non ſuffice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent quae ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, &amp; quaere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat conſilium miſer, non quomodo ero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet quod plus natum erat, ſed quomodo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruaret. <hi>Aug. ſerm. de diuit.</hi> 28.</note> Ye find a rich man immediatly after my text, whom the Lord calleth <hi>Foole:</hi> Foole <hi>this night ſhall thy ſoule be taken from thee.</hi> Wherein lay this mans folly? In that he tooke care not to lay vp for good v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but to lay vp for voluptuous vſes that ſurpluſage of eſtate which God had giuen him. Now marke what <hi>Auguſtine</hi> inferreth hereupon: If he be a foole which layes but vp his owne goods, <hi>Vos inuenite ei</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:16720:32"/> 
               <hi>nomen qui tollit aliena,</hi> find you out a fit name for him that takes away another mans. What name then may we find out? <hi>Salomon</hi> fits them with a name, Eccleſ. 3. 18. <hi>Viderem hos eſſe illis beſtias;</hi> ſo <hi>Iunius;</hi> not fooles, but beaſts. And what beaſts may they be? <hi>Kine of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan,</hi> Amos 4. 1. that is with the eaſieſt. Therefore <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanie</hi> and <hi>Nahum</hi> make them <hi>wolues, euening wolues, Lions, Lions whelpes, roaring</hi> and ramping <hi>Lions,</hi> Zeph. 3. 3. Nah. 2. 11. 12. Beaſts they are, beaſts of prey, that liue <hi>ex rapto.</hi> Not onely <hi>kine of Baſhan,</hi> that by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion trample vnder foote, but deuouring wolues, not onely <hi>trampling</hi> but <hi>tearing</hi> beaſts. How fairely were this Iland bleſt, if it were as cleare rid of theſe as it is of other wolues? How happie were it if theſe Cannibals were amongſt the ſauage Indians? How well, if theſe man-eating beaſts might be vſed as was <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> turned to graſſe? Dan. 4. 30. <hi>He was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Volunt nunc comparcere micas in alendo miſero Lazaro, cum prius effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derint in epu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonem omnes opes ſuas. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt enim e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopis arces &amp; ciuitates, ac nimis ſplendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, ac laute ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerunt eos. Nunc cum iſti alendi ſunt qui vere &amp; fideliter docent, vix mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas alioqui pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituras eis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedunt. <hi>Luther. in Gen.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>driuen from men, and did eate graſſe as the oxen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. I may not here let paſſe ſuch as are guiltie of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, impropriators of Church liuings, together with cloſe and cunning defrauders of the Miniſterie, <hi>Take ye heed and beware of couetouſneſſe.</hi> There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo ſacred and inuiolable which this Harpy da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not ſeize vpon. The patrimony of the Church is exhauſted, and they that haue enough otherwiſe will not let go their Church liuings. They whoſe forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fed and fatted the rich gluttons of Rome, think now the crums that fall vnder their tables too much for the poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> of the Goſpell. They muſt needs haue this one feather in their peacockes taile. How ſhould they maintaine that port and pompe in table, apparel, idle and prodigall expences, if this bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:16720:33"/> what if I had ſaid this ſtolne feather, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payd the Church againe? Couetouſneſſe pluckt this feather, and couetouſneſſe holdeth this feather, and telleth couetous Impropriators, that it is fitter that Gods Miniſters ſhould want maintenance, then that their horſe heeles ſhould want litter. To all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may that be ſpoken innocently which the vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeruant to his maiſter ſpake wickedly: <hi>Maiſter, I knew that thou wert an hard man, and reapedſt where thou ſowedſt not.</hi> Is not this the caſe of Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors? Are they not hard men that reape where they ſow not? If we ſow ſpirituall things, what right, what reaſon hath Couetouſneſſe to thruſt her ſickle into our harueſt, and to reape our temporall things? The world is wondrous buſie about the diſquiſition of the tenure of Tithes by what right they are due, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are cunninger in this, then in the maine funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall articles of their religion; but neuertheleſſe in the meane time there is a more neceſſarie <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> forgotten, to wit, by what right Impropriators detaine Church maintenance. Let that caſe be can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſed in the Court of conſcience, and if God ſhall there determine on their ſides, we haue done; much good do it them. I know I do but beate the ayre, but yet Iſrael muſt know his tranſgreſſions, and <hi>Iaacob</hi> his iniquities, and couetous ones heare of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations.</p>
            <p>There is alſo another ſort of ſacriledge in the cloſe purloyning and filching miniſteriall dues, which co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe hath taught falſe fingers to vſe. The Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes are taxed in the Goſpell for couetouſneſſe, and yet it were happy the world had but the Phariſes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:16720:33"/> 
               <hi>Except your righteouſneſſe exceed the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, ye ſhall not enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> Alas, how many thinke to go to heauen, that yet come farre ſhort of a Phariſees righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe? Luk. 18. 12. <hi>I,</hi> ſaith the Phariſee, <hi>pay tithe of all that euer I poſſeſſe.</hi> In which ſpeech I ſhould haue feared he had lied, had not our Sauiour elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where acknowledged ſo much of their preciſeneſſe in tithing euen vnto mint and cummin. The coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe of the Phariſees was an honeſt couetouſnes vnto the Church-robbing and Church-pilling coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe of our dayes.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It were endleſſe to follow couetouſneſſe into euery ſhop and profeſſion: therefore laſt of all, All, of all ſorts, one and another, high and low, rich and poore, old and yong, <hi>take heed and beware of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe.</hi> Take heed of it in your mutuall dealings in buying and ſelling: abuſe no mans ſimplicitie, abuſe no mans credulitie, take not the aduantage of any mans neceſſitie, but remember the ſpeech of an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Gen. 23. 15. <hi>The land</hi> is worth <hi>foure hundred ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kels of ſiluer.</hi> Take no more for a commoditie then <hi>it is worth.</hi> VVe vſe to ſay in another caſe, <hi>Caueat emptor,</hi> let the buyer beware; but here I ſay, <hi>caueat venditor,</hi> let the ſeller beware and take heed of couetouſneſſe. Take heed of falſe ballances, of <hi>a weight and a weight,</hi> Prou. 20. 10: of a weight for the hall, and a weight for the ſtall; of a weight to ſell with, and a weight to ſeale with; of a weight to ſell with, and a weight to buy with. <hi>Let no man go beyond his brother,</hi> 1. Theſſ. 4. 6. with ſwearing, proteſting, and with termes of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <hi>for God is the auenger of all theſe things.</hi> Euery
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:16720:34"/> trade is called a <hi>myſtery.</hi> It were to be wiſhed that in euery <hi>myſtery,</hi> there were not a <hi>myſtery of iniquitie</hi> found out and practiſed by the iniquitie of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe. It were a ſhame to ſend Chriſtians to ſchoole to learne honeſt dealing of Turks, and yet they boaſt that we are a fourme beneath them for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and ſquare dealing. I will rather ſend you to that rule of nature and equitie, the doctrine of the Law and the Prophets, Math. 7. 12. <hi>Whatſoeuer ye would that men ſhould do to you, euen ſo do ye to them.</hi> Buy a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ye would ſell, ſell as ye would buy, and in all you dealings take heed and beware of couetouſneſſe. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you loue God, and would be loath to <hi>breake his holy commandements;</hi> and as you feare God, and would be loath to <hi>ſuffer his heauy iudgements,</hi> the curſe of God vpon your <hi>bodies,</hi> the curſe of God vpon your <hi>goods,</hi> the curſe of God vpon the <hi>fruite of your loynes,</hi> the curſe of his euerlaſting vengeance vpon your <hi>ſoules,</hi> ſo <hi>Take heed and beware of couetouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
